<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new voyage into the northern countries being a discription of the manners, customs, superstition, buildings, and habits of the Norwegians, Laponians, Kilops, Borandians, Siberians, Samojedes, Zemblans, and Islanders : with reflexions upon an error in our geographers about the scituation and extent of Greenland and Nova Zembla.</title>
            <author>La Martinière, Pierre Martin de, 1634-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48423</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25445</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08959596</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08959596</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42107</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48423)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42107)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1288:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new voyage into the northern countries being a discription of the manners, customs, superstition, buildings, and habits of the Norwegians, Laponians, Kilops, Borandians, Siberians, Samojedes, Zemblans, and Islanders : with reflexions upon an error in our geographers about the scituation and extent of Greenland and Nova Zembla.</title>
                  <author>La Martinière, Pierre Martin de, 1634-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 153 [i.e. 155] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Starkey,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title: The voyage of Monsieur Martiniere into the northern countries.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Europe, Northern --  Description and travel.</term>
               <term>Arctic regions.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42107:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NEW VOYAGE INTO THE NORTHERN COUNTRIES Being a Diſcription of the Manners, Cuſtoms, Superſtition, Buildings, and Habits of the <hi>Norwegians, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponians, Kilops, Borandians, Sibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, Samojedes, Zemblans and Iſlanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With Reflexions upon an Error in our Geographers about the ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Extent of <hi>Greenland</hi> and <hi>Nova Zembla.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>John Starkey,</hi> at the <hi>Miter</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet</hi> near <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:42107:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42107:2"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <label>CHAP. I.</label>
               <item>THe Authors embarking at <hi>Copenha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> in a Veſſel belonging to the King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> Northern Company, and his Arrival at <hi>Chriſtiana</hi> in <hi>Norway.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. II.</label>
               <item>Particulars of the Country about <hi>Chriſtiana;</hi> with the Manners and Cuſtomes of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantry in <hi>Norway.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. III.</label>
               <item>Their way of fetching the Elks; the redicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous opinion of the Virtue of their Claw; the power and authority of the <hi>Norwegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Nobles.</item>
               <label>CHAP. IV.</label>
               <item>The Authors reimbarking at <hi>Chriſtiania;</hi> his
<pb facs="tcp:42107:3"/>arrival at <hi>Berghen,</hi> with ſome particulars of that Town.</item>
               <label>CHAP. V.</label>
               <item>The Authors reinbarking at <hi>Berghen,</hi> and his arrival at <hi>Dronthem.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. VI.</label>
               <item>The Authors departure from <hi>Dronthem</hi> to to take a view of the Silver and Copper Mines belonging to the King of <hi>Dane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. VII.</label>
               <item>Particulars of the Silver and Copper Mines in <hi>Norway.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. VIII.</label>
               <item>The entertainment the Author received from a <hi>Norwegian</hi> Peaſant in his return from the Mines.</item>
               <label>CHAP. IX.</label>
               <item>The Authors reimbarkment at <hi>Dronthem,</hi> The Mariners buying a Wind, and the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſayling in thoſe Northern Seas.</item>
               <label>CHAP. X.</label>
               <item>The Authors great danger in a Storm.</item>
               <label>CAAP. XI.</label>
               <item>The Authors arrival at <hi>Varanger</hi> in the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Laponia.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XII.</label>
               <item>The Manners, Cuſtomes, Superſtition and Habit of the <hi>Daniſh Laplanders.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42107:3"/>
               <label>CHAP. XIII.</label>
               <item>The Authors departure from <hi>Varanger</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Mourmanskoimore.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XIV.</label>
               <item>His travelling with Elks, with ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of that Beaſt.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XV.</label>
               <item>The Authors Arrival at <hi>Mourmanskoimore</hi> with ſome particulars of that Country.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XVI.</label>
               <item>The Authors Voyage into the Country of the <hi>Killopes,</hi> with their manner of Living.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XVII.</label>
               <item>The Authors Arrival in the <hi>Muſcovian Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Their Trade, Cuſtomes, and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XVIII.</label>
               <item>The Authors Arrival at <hi>Kola,</hi> the ſcituation of the Town, with the manner of their buildings and other particulars.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XIX.</label>
               <item>The Authors departure from <hi>Kola,</hi> in his return to <hi>Varanger,</hi> with the Funeral Formalities of the <hi>Muſcovian Laplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XX.</label>
               <item>The work and imployment of the <hi>Laponian</hi> Women, with other particulars of that Country.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42107:4"/>
               <label>CHAP. XXI.</label>
               <item>The Authors meeting a <hi>Laplander</hi> going a hunting.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XXII.</label>
               <item>The Authors return to <hi>Varanger,</hi> the dexterity of the <hi>Laponians</hi> in throwing their Darts ſhooting with their Bows and other particulars.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XXIII.</label>
               <item>The Authors ſailing out of the Sea of <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranger,</hi> the continuation of thisi Voyage, with other particulars.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XXIV.</label>
               <item>The meeting of the Daniſh Ships which came out of <hi>Danemark</hi> with the Author and had been ſeparated by Storm, with an account of their adventures.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XXV.</label>
               <item>The Danes reſolution to Trade to Boranday and the Authors accompanying them.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XXVI.</label>
               <item>The Stature, Habit, buildings. and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Living of the <hi>Borandians,</hi> with other particulars.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XXVII.</label>
               <item>The entertainment the <hi>Danes</hi> gave the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randians</hi> on Board, and the Authors Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age into <hi>Boranday.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42107:4"/>
               <label>CHAP. XXVIII.</label>
               <item>The ſucceſs of the Authors Voyage into <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randay,</hi> and other particulars of that Country.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XXIX.</label>
               <item>The Author meets a <hi>Borandine</hi> Lord return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from hunting, with a deſcription of their Clothes.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XXX.</label>
               <item>The Authors departure from <hi>Vitzora,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Potzora,</hi> and his traffick there.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XXXI.</label>
               <item>The Authors departure from <hi>Potzora,</hi> to go into <hi>Siberia,</hi> his meeting with five perſons of quality ſent thither into exile by the grand Czar, their miſeries and his arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val at <hi>Papinogorod.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XXXII.</label>
               <item>The Governors reception of the Daniſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants amongſt whom was the Author.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XXXIII.</label>
               <item>The <hi>Danes,</hi> and the Authors traſſick in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinogorod,</hi> the ſcituation of the Town? with the Habit, and Cuſtoms of the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berians,</hi> and <hi>Muſcovites.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XXXIV.</label>
               <item>The Authors departure from <hi>Papinogorod,</hi> towards his Ship, his paſsage thorow <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mojeſpia,</hi> with their Manners, Cuſtomes and Veſtments.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42107:5"/>
               <label>CHAP. XXXV.</label>
               <item>The Author departs from <hi>Boranday</hi> to go to <hi>Zembla,</hi> where he ſaw a Company of <hi>Zemblanes</hi> worſhiping the Sun, and two others worſhiping a wooden Idol, they called Fetitot.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XXXVI.</label>
               <item>Of a diſeaſe called the Scurvy with which the Author and moſt of the <hi>Danes</hi> in his Company were ſick.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XXXVII.</label>
               <item>Their Fiſhing for the Sea-Horſe, with the relation how two of their Sea men were ſtruck over board with one of their Tails.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XXXVIII.</label>
               <item>The boldneſs of the Bears upon the Mountains of Voygat, with the taking of certain Foul called <hi>Pingoines,</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XXXIX.</label>
               <item>Of a Zemblane which had like to have been ſurprized by the Danes, of another and his wife taken in their Canoe, with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of their Boat.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XL.</label>
               <item>The taking of another Zemblan and his wife, their Habits, Arms, and manner of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42107:5"/>
               <label>DHAP. XLI.</label>
               <item>Their departure from <hi>Zembla</hi> back again to <hi>Danemark,</hi> their Arrival in <hi>Greenland</hi> the whale Fiſhing, and the way they make their Oyl.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XLII.</label>
               <item>Their departure from <hi>Greenland,</hi> three Suns appear to them at Sea, with the relation how by the Violence of a Storm they were driven upon the Coaſt of Iſland.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XLIII.</label>
               <item>Their Arrival at <hi>Kirkebar,,</hi> their journy to Hecla, the danger the Author incurred there, the marvellous effects of two Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvins which ſpring out of that Mountain, with other particulars.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XLIV.</label>
               <item>The Habitations, Manners, Superſtitions of the Iſlanders, with other particulars.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XLV.</label>
               <item>Their departure from <hi>Cape Hori,</hi> their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival at <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> the preſent of the Horns of two Sea-Horſes, which were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for <hi>Unicorns.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XLVI.</label>
               <item>The Error about the <hi>Unicorn</hi> and the virtue of its Horn.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42107:6"/>
               <label>CHAP. XLVII.</label>
               <item>The Authors reflexions upon an Errour i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our Geographers in the ſcituation and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of <hi>Greenland</hi> and <hi>Zembla,</hi> with Obſervations upon ſuch as have writ abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Voygat</hi> and the <hi>Samojedes.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42107:6"/>
            <head>THE VOYAGE OF Monſieur MARTINIERE INTO THE <hi>Northern CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTRIES.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Author imbarking at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penhagen</hi> in a Veſsel belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks Northern-Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> and of his arrival at <hi>Chriſtiania</hi> in <hi>Norway.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the year 1647. <hi>Iredrich</hi> the third of that name, King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> out of the care of his Subjects, and advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Trade, Erected two Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies in <hi>Copenhagen</hi> (the Metropolis
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42107:7"/>of his Kingdom) one of them for <hi>Iſlande,</hi> the other for the <hi>North:</hi> which laſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving obſerv'd the advantage of their Traffick into <hi>Norway,</hi> prevailed with thoſe who were concerned in their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, about the end of <hi>February</hi> 1653. to repreſent to his Majeſty the profits would probably accrue if they carried their Trade up further than as yet they had done; and that they ſhould return doubtleſs with ſeveral Commodities which at preſent they wanted.</p>
               <p>The King having received their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was pleaſed Graciouſly to conſent, and the Company thereupon immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately cauſed three Ships to be Equip'd in order to that Voyage.</p>
               <p>Being at <hi>Copenhagen</hi> at that time, and underſtanding his Majeſty had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thoſe who were to make that Voyage, ſhould take the ſtrickteſt and moſt exact account of all the Coaſts and Places they came at, and report them with all poſſible curioſity, that thereby the Voyage might be every way beneficial, I was incouraged to addreſs my ſelf to a Friend of mine who had a principal intereſt in that affair, and to deſire his Mediation to the Company,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42107:7"/>that I might be received, and go as Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion to one of thoſe Ships.</p>
               <p>Being provided with all things neceſſary, within ſix days we Embark'd, and with a fair South-Eaſt wind ſet Sail, Coaſting by the Shoar as far as <hi>Katgat</hi> (by the French call'd <hi>Trou de chat</hi>) which is a Streight dividing the <hi>German</hi> Ocean from the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea; a place very dangerous to paſs in reſpect of the Rocks, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining in length fourty Leagues from <hi>Elſenore</hi> to <hi>Scagerhort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When we were put off of <hi>Maeſtrand</hi> (which is a ſmall Port about thirty Leagues from <hi>Copenhagen</hi>) we were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized with a fierce Wind from the North, and driven ten Leagues back again, which forc'd us to make for a Harbour, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire under the Shore to <hi>Schllot,</hi> where we lay at Shelter under the Caſtle, though it appeared to us but an old uninhabitable heap of ſtones, abandon'd for ſeveral years, and conſiderable for nothing but the Eminence of the Neighbouring Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montories.</p>
               <p>Having lyen there at Anchor two days compleat, the third before Sun-riſe by the benefit of an Eaſterly Wind, we weighed again to proſecute our Voyage.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:42107:8"/>
               <p>We had not Sail'd above four hours before we were interrupted by a North-North-Eaſt Wind which drove us from the Coaſt of <hi>Gottenburg,</hi> upon the Shore of <hi>Jutland,</hi> upon which there being mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Sands, we were forc'd to ſound every moment: Sailing in this manner, a ſudden Guſt of Wind carried us into a place where we found but three fathoms and a half Water, where we had undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly ſtruck, had not the dexterity of our Pilot turned our Ship, and by the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a favourable Blaſt, carried us in half an hours time into another place where we ſounded fifteen Fathoms and upward, which obliged us to keep the Sea with a ſide Wind as well as we were able, leaſt otherwiſe we ſhould have been forc'd back as before.</p>
               <p>We had not gain'd above two Leagues from the place where we had like to have ſtruck, before we fell into a turn of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which in ſpight of the Wind ſtopt our Veſſel on ſudden, as if we had caſt Anchor, which conſtpained us to furle all our Sails but the Mizen, and gave us twelve hours imployment to diſingage our ſelves, which notwithſtanding we could not have been able to have done,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42107:8"/>had not the Wind Veer'd to the South-South-Weſt, and given us opportunity to make uſe of the reſt of our Sails, and ſteer along the Coaſts of <hi>Bahu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having Sailed in this manner ſome Days and Nights at our Eaſe, we diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered about eight in the Morning, the Promentories of <hi>Chriſtianſand,</hi> a little Town famous for the convenience of its Port, from whence the next Night we arrived at <hi>Chriſtiania.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Particulars of the Country about <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ania,</hi> the Manners and Cuſtoms of the Peſantry in <hi>Norway.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEing entred into the Port of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ania,</hi> we immediately went a Shore, in order to the delivering of Letters we had to two Merchants which were reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent there, and Members of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who underſtanding by them that our deſign was for advancing our Trade into the North, and by the King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> conſent, received us very kindly, and treated us magnificently.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:42107:9"/>
               <p>One of thoſe Merchants finding I was a ſtranger, recommended by one of the chief of the Company, to ſhow me as much of the Country as was poſſible at that time, commanded one of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, who ſpoke <hi>French,</hi> to accompany me two or three Leagues into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and accordingly being each of us mounted on Horſe-back, early the next Morning we marched together to <hi>Wisby,</hi> a great Village ſome three Leagues from <hi>Chriſtiania</hi> built betwixt two Mountains, the houſes of Wood, without any Iron Work or Windows, the light coming in a top at a kind of a Lanthorn made of turf and ſods of Earth.</p>
               <p>The Peaſants of <hi>Norway</hi> are plain hearted, hoſpitable, given much to Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, their principal Commerce being in Herrings, Mulletts, Codds, Stock-ſiſh, and other ſorts both Salt and Dry; they are generally Slaves to the Gentry.</p>
               <p>The Women are moſt of them hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, but frickand; they love Strangers, are good Houſwives, Spin all their own Cloth, and look to their Cattel, of which they have great quantity, as in <hi>France;</hi> They have great ſtore of Game, as Elks, Staggs, Roe-Bucks, Wild-Goats, Boars,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42107:9"/>Dear, Rabbets, Hares, all kind of Fowl, beſides Otters, Beaver, Lynxes, and wild Catts of ſeveral Colours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Norway</hi> is a Mountainous Country for the moſt part, uncapable of Corn ſo much as for Bread, though they have of it good ſtore, but Tranſported from other Countries by means of their Navigation; however the ſcarcity of Arrable is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly recompenced in the plenty of their Paſture, and multitude of Woods.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Their way of Hunting the Elkes. The Ridiculous Opinion af the Virtue of their Claw, the Power and Authority of the <hi>Norwegian</hi> Nobleſs.</head>
               <p>IN our return from <hi>Wisby</hi> to <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ania,</hi> we were met by a Gentleman and his two Servants going a Hunting with their Dogs at their Heels. The Gentleman knowing the perſon who was with me, ask'd him if we would divert our ſelves, and ſee the Hunting of an Elke, which we accepted, and marching with him about a quarter of a League,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42107:10"/>we met one of the Gentlemans Hunts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with ten or twelve Country-fellows which conducted us about three quarters of a League further into a great Wood, ſo thick, we were forced to leave our Horſes with one of his Servants, and go in on foot.</p>
               <p>The Game being prepared the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by his Servants, we had not paſſ'd two Piſtol ſhot into the Wood, when we ſaw a large <hi>Elke</hi> running before us and fall down on a ſudden without any noiſe of a Gun, nor indeed ſhot; the ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the ſight, cauſed me to inquire of my Guid what might be the reaſon, and he told me it was a ſort of Falling-ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs peculiar to that kind of Beaſt, from whence among them it had its denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>Elend,</hi> (as they call them) being as <hi>miſerable</hi> with us. This Creature was about the bigneſs of a large Horſe, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died like a Stagg, but broader, its Leggs longer, his foot large and cloven, his head large, and Velvet; Were it not for this Diſtemper it would be no eaſie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to take them, which I perceived by this Gentleman, who when he had kill'd this in its Fit, undertook another, and ran it two full hours without any effect,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42107:10"/>nor had he ever taken it, had it not fallen down with the ſame Diſeaſe as the former, after it had ſlain three of his Dogs with its fore feet; which put the poor Gentleman into ſuch a fume, he would Hunt no more that day. He ſent for a little Chariot to a Farm-houſe he had about half a League off, to carry home his <hi>Elke</hi> to his own houſe, which was built <hi>all antique,</hi> as the reſt of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try are, to which he would needs have us bear him Company, and entertained us handſomely when we came there.</p>
               <p>The Gentleman underſtanding by my Camerade I was a Stranger, recommended by ſeveral of the <hi>Norway</hi> Company at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penhagen,</hi> obliged him to give me (as a Teſtimony of his Friendſhip) the two hinder feet of the <hi>Elke</hi> he kill'd laſt, and to let me know it was a Soveraign reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt the Falling-ſickneſs, which which when he delivered I could not but ſmile, and deſir'd him to let the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man know I wondered much the Foot having the virtue he mentioned, the poor <hi>Elkes</hi> could not cure themſelves, ſeeing they had them always about them. The Gentleman reflecting upon what I ſaid, fell a laughing himſelf, and told me I had
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42107:11"/>reaſon, he told me he had try'd it many times upon People in that Diſtemper, but without any benefit; and ingeniouſly confeſſ'd he look'd upon that virtue, but as pretended, and a meer popular Error.</p>
               <p>The next morning early, having broken our Faſt with the Gentleman, we gave him thanks for our Entertainment, and taking our leaves we arriv'd at <hi>Chriſtiania.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having in the precedent Chapter ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Manners of the Peaſants, I ſhall in this, give the Gentry this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, They are Wiſe, Wary, and yet Brave; they poſſeſs all the great Offices of that Kingdom, are Soveraign in their particular Territories, Tyrants to their Tenants, good Soldiers both by Land and by Sea, and addicted to Travel.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:42107:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The Authors going on Board again at <hi>Chriſtiania;</hi> his arrival at <hi>Bergen</hi> in <hi>Norway,</hi> with ſome particulars of that Town.</head>
               <p>HAving ſtayed four or five days at <hi>Chriſtiania,</hi> we took our leaves of our two Merchants of the Northern Company, who confirmed our Orders, and wiſh'd us a good Voyage. Being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imbarqued we weighed Anchor, got out of the Port, and purſued our Journey by the favour of a North-Eaſt Wind, which which continued as far as <hi>Stafanger,</hi> where we were taken with ſo great a Calm, that (not able to advance) we were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged (to entertain our ſelves, and paſs away the time) to betake our ſelves to Fiſhing. The Coaſt of <hi>Norway</hi> abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo plentifully with Fiſh of all ſorts, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>  took them in ſuch Multitudes, as made us keep Lent, though at another time of the year.</p>
               <p>The Calm having continued us in that place five entire days, on the ſixth at Night, we were befriended with a freſh
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42107:12"/>Gale from South-Eaſt, which in no long time carried us to <hi>Bergen</hi> whither we were to go, and diſcharge our ſelves of ſuch Merchandize as was deſigned to that place.</p>
               <p>Being entred into the Harbour (which is one of the beſt in <hi>Europe</hi>) and being come to an Anchor, while they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lading. I took a view of Town, which is abont the bigneſs of <hi>Abeville,</hi> part of it built high upon the Rocks, and part of it on the Shore. Tis now conſiderable principally for its Trade, though ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Arch-Biſhoprick, but ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in thoſe parts, that is aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Biſhops Palace is given to three Hans Towns, <hi>Hamborough, Lubech,</hi> and <hi>Bremen,</hi> as a Store-houſe for their goods, and ſeveral priviledges confirm'd to them by the King of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Magazine or Store-houſe is called the Cloiſter, and the Factors which inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit it Monks, though they are not tyed to any habit, nor obſerve any Laws but celibacy, which when they are not able to keep, or are otherwiſe inclined to marry, they are obliged to quit and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelves to ſome other, but yet with power reſerv'd to Trade and Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42107:12"/>with their Brethren as they think good. Their chief Traffick is in Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, Mullets, God, and Stoco-fiſh, which is round and dry, and ſold in great quantities in <hi>Muſcovie, Swede, Poland, Danemark, Germany, Holland,</hi> and other Countries,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The Authors reimbarking at <hi>Bergen,</hi> and his arrival at <hi>Dronthem.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS ſoon as they had unladen the goods conſign'd to that place, I went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, and in half an hours time the Wind being come about gently to the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt, our Maſter Weigh'd, and making what Sail was convenient, we cruiſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Coaſt of <hi>Dronthem,</hi> where half our Lading was to be delivered to the Super-intendant of the Silver and Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Mines, to make proviſion of Beer and Bread for the uſe of the Miners.</p>
               <p>We had not paſſed above half the way, before the Wind increaſed ſo faſt upon us, that in fifteen or ſixteen hours we came up with <hi>the Store,</hi> but in an inſtant it
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42107:13"/>abated, and we found our ſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calm'd.</p>
               <p>There being nothing more tedious to the Sea-men then a Calm, not knowing how to imploy themſelves, they fell again to their old recreation of Fiſhing, and took ſuch quantitie of a ſort they call <hi>Klipen-fiſh,</hi> they were conſtrained to Salt great part of them, which ſtood us in good ſtead afterwards.</p>
               <p>This Fiſh is a kind of Mullet, but big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then that they take in New-found Land, which by reaſon it keeps cloſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Rocks, is by the <hi>Germans</hi> called <hi>Klippe-fiſh,</hi> as much as to ſay in that Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, Fiſh of the Rocks.</p>
               <p>Having been becalm'd for ſome days, a Weſt South-weſt Wind aroſe, which aſſiſted very well for our gaining of <hi>Dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them,</hi> where we arrived about three days after.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:42107:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The Authors departure from <hi>Dronthem</hi> to take a view of the Silver and Copper-Mines, which belong to the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS ſoon as we were landed, we went to deliver our Letters to the Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant General of the Mines, and made it our requeſt he would order our Grain to be received as ſoon as was poſſible; but he told us his Officers were all at the Mines, for ſome of whom he muſt ſend on purpoſe before it could be received, which when I underſtood, I entreated our Maſter I might be permitted to go along with the Meſſenger, and he granted my deſire.</p>
               <p>The next Morning betimes the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and I were both of us on Horſe-back, and rode together as far as <hi>Steckby,</hi> a great Town about ſix Leagues from <hi>Dronthem,</hi> where we judg'd it beſt to take up, as well becauſe Night was coming on (though but three a Clock) as that we were to paſs a great Wood full of Woolfs and Bears, and Lynxes, which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42107:14"/>being very fierce, made our Travel in the Night more dangerous then ordinary.</p>
               <p>The next Morning by Sun-riſing we left <hi>Steckby,</hi> purſuing our journey to the Mines. About Night we arrived at the forges, where according to the cuſtom of the Country, we were entertained with Tobacco, Strong-waters, and Beer, with all which we were forced to debauch. I found there a <hi>Commis,</hi> who having waited upon a <hi>Norway</hi> Gentleman in <hi>France,</hi> ſpake good French. I told him how my Curioſity had invited me to ſee the Mines, I deſir'd his favour to aſſiſt me in ſeeing them, which he promiſed me next day, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter two hours ſmart drinking we went to bed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:42107:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Particulars of the Silver and Copper Mines in <hi>Norway.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE next Morning by break of day the Meſſenger with whom I came, departed with a <hi>Commis</hi> for <hi>Drontham,</hi> having left me in charge with one of the Maſter Miners, who being to follow the day after, was to bring me along with him. As ſoon I was up, I went out to find out my <hi>Commis</hi> which ſpake French, who had provided a good break-faſt as well for himſelf and me, as for the Maſter Miner my Governour; and whilſt we were at it, the <hi>Commis</hi> deſired the ſaid Maſter that he would carry me down into the Mines, and let me ſee them work.</p>
               <p>When we had broke our faſt, we paſſed about fifty paces from the Forges, which are built upon an high Mountain near the mouth of the Mine; upon the Edge of it is an Engine called a Crane, which is turn'd by two men by the help of two Wheels, one going into one, the other into the other, and turning them about, they drew up great peices from the Mine,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42107:15"/>ſometimes in Ore, ſometimes in Earth, as they do your Square-ſtone and Pot-Earth at <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Maſter Miner and I put our ſelves into a Tub of Wood, hoop'd about with Iron, and Ropes faſtned to them, in which we were let down into the Mine, above fifty fathom deep.</p>
               <p>Being come down I could not imagine my ſelf any where but in Hell, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing to be ſeen but dark diſmal Holes, great Fires, and the Miners like ſo many Devils, clad all of them in black Leather, with a hood of the ſame ſtuff over their heads, in faſhion of what our Prieſts wear in Winter, it was cut ſharp towards the bottom, and the other broad end faſtned over their Noſe (to preſerve them againſt fumes) and an apron of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Their work in theſe Mines is ſeveral, ſome cutting and chizelling the Ore, others probing with their inſtruments, as well to find out the Copper Veins, as to diſcover the Water, which ſometimes ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hid in the ground, upon the leaſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, breake out with ſo violent an Erup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as would drown them all, were they not exceedingly careful.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:42107:15"/>
               <p>The Maſter Miner who accompanied me down, perceiving I was affrighted, and ſurprized with a ſtrange chilneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, rung the Bell to give notice above to draw us up again which they did in almoſt as little time as we went down, and then return'd to the Forges, where we found my French Interpreter atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding us at Dinner.</p>
               <p>After Dinner the Commis cauſed three Horſes to be ſadled for himſelf, the Maſter Miner, and me, to go ſee the Silver Mines, about two Leagues beyond, where being arriv'd, we alighted at the Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants houſe, who received us very kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, preſenting each of us with a good glaſs of ſtrong Waters, he having drank firſt a brimmer to bid us welcome, and after that he treated us with Tobacco and Beer.</p>
               <p>Having treated us in this manner, he conducted us to the Forges which are about a quarter of a League from his houſe, much of the ſame nature with the Copper Forges, with ſeveral people at work, ſome ſeparating, ſome waſhing, ſome melting, others refining, and others coining for the ſervice of his Majeſty.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:42107:16"/>
               <p>From the Forges we paſſed to the Mine, which is in a Mountain over againſt them, into which I went down with the Maſter, as I did into the Copper Mines. I found no difference betwixt them, the holes, fires and habits, with the manner and time of working being exactly the ſame; that is to ſay, in the Spring and Fall they work three hours in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, and three in the afternoon, in ſummer four before dinner, and four after; the reſt they rejoyce, dancing to their Ho-boys Violins, and other Inſtruments, as it was my fortune to ſee them the firſt night I came to the Copper Forges; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Winter quarter they work not at all, but are paid as when they work, at the rate of five ſhillings a day.</p>
               <p>Having ſeen all the Silver Mines, we return'd to the Intendants lodging, where we ſupp'd and lay. The next Morning having broke our faſt, we took leave of our Intendant, and mounting on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, we dined at the Copper Mines, from whence, having taken leave of my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis which ſpoke French, the Maſter Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and I departed in our journey to <hi>Dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:42107:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The Entertainment the Author received of a <hi>Northwegian Peaſant,</hi> in his return from the Mines to <hi>Dronthem.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE had not trsvelled above two Leagues and a half, before we were overtaken by the Night, and forc'd to take our ſelves to the houſe of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-man of the Maſter Miners acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which was not far off, who to ſpeak truth, received us very handſomly, conſidering his condition, giving us for a Supper a brace of Pheaſants: and a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hare which he had killed after an hours chaſe, (which is free in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to all People) beſides Beer, To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco, and Strong-waters when we came in.</p>
               <p>After Supper we fell a ſmoaking again like Dragons, and drank Strong-waters for a better or a worſe, and continued our Frolick till it was well near Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <p>The poor Peaſant ſeeing the Maſter Miner had made himſelf drunk to do him an honour, was ſo tranſported with the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42107:17"/>kindneſs, he thought he could do no leſs then be as drunk as his Gueſt, to which purpoſe having ſufficiently ſoaked it, a pallat was laid in the middle of the room, they laid upon it, and I laid my ſelf by them in expectation of day.</p>
               <p>The Sun was up, and the Maſter Miner and his Bed-fellow in a moſt profound ſleep. My deſign being to be at <hi>Dronthem</hi> that Night, I cauſed the Horſes and break-faſt to be got rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and then with much ado wak'd them; we ſat down, fed as heartily as we could, and then taking leave of our Hoſt; we got on Horſe-back, and managed the buſineſs ſo well, we got to <hi>Dronthem</hi> before Night.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:42107:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The Author goes on Board again at <hi>Dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them.</hi> The Mariners conſtrained to buy a Wind, and the danger of Sailing in the Northern Sea.</head>
               <p>TWo days after, having unladen what was there to be delivered, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived what proviſions the Intendant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral had Orders to procure us, the Wind being favourable, we went on Board, and ſome few hours after, ſet Sail in order to our Voyage.</p>
               <p>For ſome days togethep we Sailed very happily, till we came under the Arctick Circle, where we were ſuddenly becalm'd, not far from the Coaſts.</p>
               <p>Being informed that the People which inhabit about the ſaid Circle, as well as they which live about the Coaſts of <hi>Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> are for the moſt part Sorcerers, and diſpoſe of the Wind as they pleaſe, we cauſed our Sloop to be prepared, and ſome of our Sea-men went on Shore to the next Village they could meet with, to purchaſe one for us. They inquired for the beſt Necromancer the Town did
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42107:18"/>afford; and having addreſſed themſelves to him, they told him whither they were bound, and deſired him to furniſh them with a Wind would carry them to <hi>Mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manskoimore.</hi> He told them he could not, and that his power extended no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the Promontories of <hi>Rouxella;</hi> which place being a conſiderable diſtance, and not far from the North-Cape, they thought good to take him along into their Ship, and make their bargain with him there. To which end they made bold with a ſmall Fiſher-boat they found there, and putting him and three of his Camerades into it, they convey'd them a board, where we bargained with him for a pound of Tobacco, and ten Crowns in Silver, for which they faſtned to a corner of our fore-maſt Sail, a piece of Linnen Cloth about a foot long, and four fingers broad, in which having tyed three knots, they told us that would do, and then entred into their Skip to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
               <p>They were no ſooner out of the Veſſel, but our Maſter untyed the firſt knot in the Ragg, and immediately we had a Weſt South-weſt Wind, the pleaſanteſt in the World, which darried us and the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42107:18"/>Ships of our Company, thirty Leagues beyond <hi>Maelſtroom</hi> before we had occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to unty another.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Maelſtroom</hi> is the greateſt Whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pool in all the Norwegian Sea, in which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ships periſh by coming too near it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are aware; for which reaſon ſuch as know the danger, and are better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Rode, ſtand off eight or ten Leagues higher into the Sea, to avoid a great number of Rocks, and other tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of water which lye out ſix or feaven leagues from the Shore.</p>
               <p>The wind vering and coming about to the <hi>North,</hi> our Maſter open'd the ſecond knot, and it became favourable again as ſar as the Mountains of <hi>Rouxilla,</hi> where we had no fooner doubled the point, but our Compaſs varied on a ſuddain, and the Needle went back above ſix points, which made us conjecture there were Loadſtones in thoſe Mountains, whether there were or not, this I am ſure, had not our Pilot been expert, we had miſtaken our way.</p>
               <p>Suppoſing the reſt of our Ships in the ſame condition, our Pilat laid by his Compaſs, and hanging out a flag upon his Mizen, he gave a ſignal to the others to follow him, that place being very well
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42107:19"/>known to him, in reſpect he had made ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral voyages thither with the Dutch, who ſail only by their Sea-Chart when they come in that place.</p>
               <p>Two whole days and nights we conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in this perplexity, after which being got at ſome diſtance from the Mountains, our Needle return'd to its Center, which gave us to underſtand we were not far from the Cape, but the wind beginning to ſlacken, our Maſter unty'd the third knot, which was the laſt he had.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Their great danger in a Storm.</head>
               <p>THe laſt knot being unty'd, it was not lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before there aroſe a North North-Weſt wind, ſo furious and violent it ſeemed to us as if the whole Heavens were falling down upon our heads, and God by a juſt vengeance intended our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination for the ſin we had committed in giving car to thoſe Sorcerers; for not being able to keep up our ſayls, we were forc'd to abandon our ſelves to the mercy of the waves, which hurry'd us with ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement an agitation, we expected no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42107:19"/>but to broken in pieces and drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>Being not above 12. Leagues from the ſhore, and with much labour ſcarce able to keep the Sea, yet we could not imagine the power of the ſtorm could have driven us thither in ſpight of our teeth, but we reckon'd without our Hoſt, for the third day about noon there aroſe ſo fierce and ſuddain a ſtorm, as blowed us among the Rocks, and daſh'd us preſently upon one of them, about thirty Leagues upward of the Cape, and four from the Shore. The whole Ship fetch'd a great skriek, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man fell to his prayers, believing that day would be the laſt of our lives. The truth is, I nor none of the reſt were ever more in danger, all expecting when our Veſſel ſhould ſplit. But by extraordinary providence the greatneſs and ſorce of the waves diſingaged us, and threw us near a Piſtol-Shot off of the Rock, without any conſiderable prejudice more than a ſmall hole in the Keel, which took a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle water, and ſome few boards looſn'd and ſplinter'd, which kept us cloſe to our Pump, and gave us conſtant imployment.</p>
               <p>The fourth day the Storm being abated and the sky cleer, not ſeeing the reſt of our
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42107:20"/>Company, we were much troubled, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving them caſt away, however that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred us not from following our voyage, the wind being in ſome meaſure favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to it.</p>
               <p>Finding our Ship leak, and our labour in pumping great and continual, it was thought beſt to make for ſome convenient Harbour, where we might Caulk, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, but the North Sea being full of Rocks all along upon the Coaſts, and their Crceks and Ports by that means inacceſſible, we were conſtrain'd to keep out two days lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at Sea, before we could put in ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But the fourth in the morning we were got upon the Coaſts of <hi>Werdhus</hi> a Caſtle the <hi>Danes</hi> have built, in which they have a Garriſon and a Commiſs. to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive all Duties from ſuch as paſs or repaſs from <hi>Archangel</hi> in the White Sea, which Officer permitted us very civilly to paſs without ſending aboard us, knowing us to be <hi>Danes</hi> by our flag, and the ſalute we gave him when we paſſed by the Caſtle, and entred into the Sea of <hi>Varanger, where we came to an Anchor, about half a League from the Town.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:42107:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> The Authors arrival at <hi>Varanger</hi> in that <hi>Laponia</hi> which is under the Dominion of the King of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS ſoon as we were entred we put our Shallop into the Sea, but there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none in our whole Crew that had any knowledge of the place (which appeared very ſavage and horrid) ſeven of us beſide the Maſter, well Arm'd, ventured a little way up, to ſee if we could find any place more commodious, or any Inhabitants that could give us their aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Having paſſed about half a League, we came into a Town well Inhabited, with a good Harbour the Town was called <hi>Varan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger;</hi> the people were amazed to ſee us come in in that equipage, ſtaring and gaping up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us with admiration.</p>
               <p>Our Maſter knowing they ſpake the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the north, which he underſtood very well, demanded civily if they would permit him to bring our Veſſel into the Harbour and repair it.</p>
               <p>Being informed we were Merchants and our buſineſs fiſhing for <hi>Wall-Rus</hi> (which is Sea-Horſe with us) they offered both their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42107:21"/>Port and aſſiſtance which we accepted, and having viewed the Port, we returned to our Veſſel, and weighing immediately, we put in, and fell a lightning, diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves of our Ballaſt (which was Sand) with ſome cheſts of Tobacco, and certain Balls of Linnen cloth, which we carryed to Barter with the Natives when occaſion was offered.</p>
               <p>When we had unladen, we took our Cloth and Tobacco and put them into a Caban near the ſhore, which our Maſter and the Commiſſioners for the Merchants cauſed to be made faſt and ſecured.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:42107:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of the manners Cuſtoms ſuperſtitions and Habits of the Daniſh <hi>Laplanders.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO create a good intelligence with theſe people, which as I ſaid before were <hi>Laponians,</hi> we made them a preſent of ſome pieces of Tobacco in the Rol, which they received with as much joy as if they had been wedges of Gold, and to requite us they requiteus with ſuch things as they had, which indeed was a ſort of dryed Fiſh they eat in ſtead of Bread; the fleſh of <hi>Elks</hi> (which is an animal to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> found only in <hi>Laponia, Boranday, Samojespi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; Siberia</hi>) Bears and other Wild-Beaſt; which we had never ſeen before. They gave us likewiſe a certain freſh Fiſh boil'd up without ſalt, which they dipped ſome of them in the oyl of another Fiſh, others in a ſharp liquor they uſed inſtead of their drink. But none of us approving their <hi>Ragous,</hi> we were glad to betake our ſelves to the proviſions we had brought with us which was honeſt Biſket and ſalt Beef, which we preſented them; but they no
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42107:22"/>ſooner put them in their mouths, but they ſpit them out again, with as much abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination as we had done theirs, however in complaſancy they drank of our bear and ſtrong waters, but not with the guſt and delight they ſwill down their own, which they make of fair water, Juniper-Berries, and another berry like lintels, (whoſe name I have forgot) of which ſort they have very great plenty, growing as the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niper does) among the leaves of a plant like our <hi>Fearn</hi> but thicker and higher, and what I could never find in any Herba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt. They have a kind of ſtrong water too which they diſtil with a Limbeck of Copper <hi>in balnio Mariae,</hi> putting in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain grain which gives it the ſame ſtrength and intoxication as ours, and their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary drink is not for that inferiour to our wine.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Laplanders</hi> (though they are <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans</hi> by prfeſſion, and have their Prieſts to inſtruct them) yet they are ſtrangely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded by the Devil, being moſt of them Witches, and ſo ſuperſtitious, if they meet any Creature they fancy unfortunate, they will run back to their Cabanes and not come out again all that day. If when they are fiſhing, they throw their Nets, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42107:22"/>draw up but one Fiſh, they look upon it as a dangerous Omen, home they go, and no more fiſhing for that day.</p>
               <p>The Men and Women are low, but ſtrong ſet, and active, their face broad, flat nos'd, and tawny, but not ſo much as others more North, their eyes are little like Hogs eyes, their eye-brows large and reaching almoſt to their Temples; they are heavy and ſtupid, without any civility, very laſcivious eſpecially the women, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting themſelves to all commers, as often as they can do it with ſecurity from their husbands.</p>
               <p>Their habit is various, ſometimes of a coarſe ſort of cloth, but generally of <hi>Elks</hi> skin with the hair on the out-ſide, their ſtockings of the ſame, their ſhoos of a fiſh skin with the ſcaleson, like ſlippers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hinder quarter or Ears. Their heads are dreſſed like the <hi>Norwegiens,</hi> their hair in two plats, one hanging upon one ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the other upon the other, a Hood or Coife of coarſe Canvas over it, which is all the linnen they wear; others a piece of fur a little broader than ones hand, which they tie behind their heads, <hi>ala Egiptien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The mens clothes are all of <hi>Elks</hi>-skin,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42107:23"/>dreſſed with the hair outwards; the chief of them is a Waſt-coat made ſhort, to the middle of their Thighs; with a pair of Bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees of the ſame, their Stockings are all one, with a ſort of Boots made of the skins of Fiſh, ſo cleverly that though they ſeem clumſy and great, the ſeams are not eaſily to be found. Many of them there are who wear no Boots, but Shooes like the women; upon their heads they have a kind of round Cap, like our Seamen, made of <hi>Elks</hi>-skins with the hair upon it, lined at the edges with a piece of a <hi>Fox</hi> skin, ſometimes white and ſometimes grey. Their houſes are much at the ſame rate with the inhabitants of <hi>Chriſtiania,</hi> having no other light but what comes in at top.</p>
               <p>They have no Beds to ly upon at night, no more than the reſt of their neighbours, the <hi>Moſcovian Laplanders, Borandians, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiedes, Siberians, Zemblians, Iſlanders,</hi> and other people of the North; they diſplay themſelves fairly in the middle of the room upon <hi>Bear</hi>-skins, where they ly higgledy piggledy, Maſter, Miſtreſs, Children, men and Maid-ſervants alltogether without any ſcruple, and when they riſe in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, they return the skins to their old pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces very orderly.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:42107:23"/>
               <p>Every houſe has belonging to it a great black Cat, of which they make great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, talking and diſcourſing to it as it were a rational Creature. They do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but they firſt communicate with their Cat, as believing ſhe aſſiſts them high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in all their enterprizes. Every night they go out of their <hi>Cabanes</hi> to conſult their dear puſs; nor can they expect a bleſſing upon their ſports either Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Fiſhing, Fouling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unleſs their good Angel goes along with them, which though I have ſeen many of them, and all have the figure of a Cat, yet by the dreadfulneſs of their looks, I did and do ſtill think they can be nothing but De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:42107:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> The Authors departure from <hi>Varanger</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Mourmanskoimore.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving unladen our Veſſel the next day after our arrival at <hi>Varanger,</hi> the people of the Town were very helpful to us in the turning and refitting of it, for the Maſter finding it in a much worſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than he imagined, he deſired the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants to find him out wood that might be proper to repair it, which they did up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Mountain not far off, and brought it to him when they had done.</p>
               <p>The Commiſs. for the Merchants percieving it would take up ſome time before our ſhip could be fitted, thought it convenient to paſs higher into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and ſee if they had any thing there, to barter for his Commodities: with this deſign he made choice of me and two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to bear him Company, and the next morning (the 12 of <hi>March</hi>) we took our Tobacco and linnen cloth to traffique, our biſcuit and ſalt meat for our provant, and with three of the Natives (as well to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry our proviſion as to conduct us) we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42107:24"/>thorough Woods, Mountains val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> till about four a clock in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening, at which time we deſcribed two great and fierce white Bears m king to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, which gave us no little appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion.</p>
               <p>Our Convoy percieving our fright, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed us not to be troubled, telling us if they ſhould make at us, we had no more to do but to ſtand to our Arms and they would be gon; and for experiment ſake we fell to fitting our flint, and priming our pan, which they no ſooner percieved but (either affrighted with the flaſhing of pan or the ſmell of the power) away they ran, and we heard of them no more, about an hour after coming down a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, we diſcovered about a dozen houſes at a good diſtance from one another, and a little farther two herds of creatures like Stags, which our Guides told us were <hi>Elks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being got to that Town, they brought us to a Cabane where we repos'd our ſelves being much tyred by the length and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſomneſs of our journey, and the weight of the Luggage we brought along with us. The firſt thing we did, we preſented our Landlord with a piece of Tobacco, which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:42107:25"/>pleas'd him exceedingly, and he told us he had not had ſuch a preſent in nine Months before, and to recompence our kindneſs, he gave us ſome of his <hi>Aqua-vitae,</hi> a piece of freſh <hi>Elks</hi> fleſh, and dryed Fiſh, which we diſtributed to our guides, and feaſted them, whil'ſt we made ſhift with our own proviſions; after which we laid our ſelves down upon certain large white Bear skins and went to ſleep according to the mode of that Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> How we were drawn by the <hi>Elks</hi> in <hi>Lapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> and ſome particulars of that Beaſt.</head>
               <p>HAving got up the next morning we deſired to know of our Hoſt if he had nothing to truck againſt our cloth and Tobacco: he told us he had skins, both <hi>Wolf, Fox, White Squirrel,</hi> &amp;c. and his Neighbours had more which he believed they would willingly Barter. We deſired to ſee them and they brought them out to us and with them four ſuits made of <hi>Elk</hi>-skin to keep us from the cold, of which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42107:25"/>they gave us ſome for our Tobacco, and ſome for our Cloth.</p>
               <p>There being no more traffique to be had there, we intreated our Landlord to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh us with <hi>Elks</hi> to carry us farther into the Country, which we no ſooner pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, but ſtepping out of the door, he took his Horn, and blew for the <hi>Elks,</hi> which came to him forthwith, to the number of fourteen or fifteen. He took ſix of them harneſſed them, and then put them into ſix Sledges, made in the faſhion of a <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dela,</hi> ſupported by ſix little Rafters, faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to a piece of wood about two foot longer than the Sledge; we put our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities into one of them, and having paid in Tobacco two of our Guides, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed them, we retained the third (who had been in the other <hi>Laponia</hi> under the Government of the Duke of <hi>Muſcovie,</hi> and underſtood their Language well, as alſo the Country and Language of the <hi>Killopes</hi>) to conduct us as a Guide.</p>
               <p>Having placed our ſelves every man in his Sledge in the <hi>Lapland</hi> habits which we had bought of the Natives, we were each of us covered with a Bear-skin, having, them faſtned us to with a large thong of <hi>Elk</hi>-Leather to our Charriot, they gave us two
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42107:26"/>glaſſes of <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> a piece, and then put a ſhort <hi>Battoon</hi> (with an Iron-pike at the end of it) into every ones hand, to eaſe our ſelves, and prevent being turned over at every ſtone or ſtump of a Tree we came at.</p>
               <p>When we were juſt ready to depart, our Landlord to whom the <hi>Elks</hi> did belong, mumbled out certain words into the ears of every one of them, telling them as (we ſuppoſed) whither they were to carry us, upon which they gave ſuch a ſpring, we thought we had had ſo many Divels in our Sledges, and at that rate they carried us over Mountains and Valleys out of all bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Roads, till about ſeaven a clock at night, at which time they brought us to a large Country-Village ſcituate among the Mountains near a great Lake, and then ſtopped at the fourth ho uſe we came to, ſtamping all of them with one of their feet as it were to give notice of their arrival. The Maſter of the houſe taking the alarm came forth with his ſervants to unty us. One of them brought a <hi>Juniper</hi> Can of ſtrong waters, out of which he gave each of us a litttle cup (made of the wood) full, to drink, and refreſh our ſelves before we alighted, underſtanding by our Guid we
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42107:26"/>were in no little diſorder, as being not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to ſo ſwift and violent a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance.</p>
               <p>Theſe Creatures both Male and Female have their horns ſomething loftier then a ſtag, more crooked, ſhaggy, and not ſo many little horns, they are of the ſame co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour with a Stag, their Slot cloven, and as large as a good Ox. They feed altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon <hi>Moſs,</hi> which is very plentifull all over the Country. The females are milked as our Cowes, of which the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants make very good Butter and Cheeſe. They faſten theſe <hi>Elks</hi> to two poles tyed faſt to the Sledges with thongs of <hi>Elks</hi>-skin, not unlike our harneſs for our Coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, with which they draw them with incredible ſwiftneſs, carrying them direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the places appointed, without any trouble to govern or guide them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:42107:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> The Authors arrival at <hi>Mourmanskoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> with ſome particulars of that Country.</head>
               <p>BEing alighted from our Carriages, we went into the Houſe which we found like the reſt of that Country, very little, low, and covered with the bark of Trees, having no light but what came in at the top of the houſe as in <hi>Norway.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Laplanders</hi> have their habits ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing longer than thoſe from whence we came, they are made likewiſe, of the skins of <hi>Elks,</hi> with the hair outwards; the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are in the ſame dreſs, their hair breid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the other, with a round Bonnet upon their head, of the ſame skin with the reſt of their clothes.</p>
               <p>We gave the Maſter as ſoon as we came in a piece of Tobacco in the Roll about the length of two fingers, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieved very kindly we gave every one of his Neighbours another, for our better ſecurity, as percieving them more ſavage than any we had ſeen; after which we ſupped upon the proviſions we brought with us,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42107:27"/>and our Guide upon his dry'd Fiſh, and <hi>Elk</hi> fleſh baked without ſalt. Inquiring of him how many Leagues we had come that day, he told us about thirty, and that we were in the Country of <hi>Mourmanſkoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> in which the Inhabitants ſpeaking another Language than they did in <hi>Varan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> we could not underſtand them a word.</p>
               <p>After we had ſupped, we laid our ſelves down fairly upon their bears kins, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their mode, and went to ſleep, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving before trucked our clothes for theirs, which were ſomething longer, and a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Squirrels</hi> skins (which they had ready by them) for ſome of our Tobacco.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:42107:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> The Authors Voyage into the Country of the <hi>Killoppes,</hi> and their manner of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</head>
               <p>THE next day being the 14. of <hi>May,</hi> we deſired our Interpreter to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint our Hoſt that we would have him provide us Sledges to go up farther into the Country, which he did, and the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours came to help us; bringing their <hi>Aqua-Vitae</hi> along with them, to drink with us before we departed.</p>
               <p>They put ſix <hi>Elks</hi> into ſix Sledges, into one of which we put our goods, and mounted the reſt our ſelves, after which they covered and faſtned us as before, and having whiſper'd their directions into the Ears of their <hi>Elks,</hi> away they went with a vengeance; hurrying us along almoſt full ſpeed till two in the afternoon before we came near any Houſe, and about three they brought us to a little Village of ſome eight houſes, built upon a high Mountain near a great Wood, where they ſtopp'd on a ſuddain, and made us believe we were
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:42107:28"/>at our journies end, but no body coming to us, we were forced to bait our <hi>Elks</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Moſs,</hi> (which was there in good ſtore) our ſelves upon our ſalt meat and biſcuit, and our Interpreter upon his Fiſh, making bold now and then with a Bottle of Strong-waters our laſt Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord had given us.</p>
               <p>Having reſted a Matter of an hour, our Guide (who underſtood to make an <hi>Elk</hi> march as well as the beſt of them) had much ado to perſwade ours any farther; that being the place (as it ſeem'd) to which they were directed, which put the poor man upon a great many odd Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, going five or ſix times alone in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wood, and then back again, ſtill whiſpering into their Ears at his return, and all would ſcarce do, at length they were good natur'd, and went on, but not with that ſpeed and alacrity they came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>We asked him how it came to paſs we found no body in that Village, and he told us in thoſe parts it was no wonder; that we were now in the Country of the <hi>Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopes,</hi> which are a ſort of <hi>Laplanders</hi> leſs civiliz'd than any of the reſt, changing their quarters very often, to avoid the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42107:29"/>Company of ſtrangers, and living wholly upon hunting without any Communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with other people.</p>
               <p>Following our journey, we went down a high Mountain about nine at night, and percieved four <hi>Kiloppes</hi> returning from hunting in four Sledges drawn with <hi>Elks</hi> like ours, but as ſoon as they ſaw us they made another way, at the bottom of the Mountain we entred into a great Wood, and being got about the middle, we, heard ſtrange yellings and Cries, but ſaw no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <p>Being out of the Wood, deſcending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Mountain, we percieved a Village to which our Cattel carried us, and took up our Lodgings as they pleaſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, where being refreſhed with our own proviſions, we went to ſleep as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:42107:29"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> The Authors arrival in the <hi>Muſcovian Lapland,</hi> their Trade, Manners and Cuſtoms.</head>
               <p>AS ſoon as we had ſhaked our ears next Morning, we inquired of our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter how many Leagues we had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the day before, and he told us at leaſt forty (which are about a hundred and ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſuch as are betwixt <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>Lyons</hi>) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of their Leagues being more than a <hi>German</hi> League, which make four times as much as a League about <hi>Paris,</hi> and are between ſix and ſeaven miles of ours, a Horſman very well mounted not being able to ride above five of them in a day; and he told us moreover we were then in a part of <hi>Laponia</hi> which was under the <hi>Czar</hi> of <hi>Muſcovy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As we were drinking with the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, and ſmoaking of Tobacco, we cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s'd him to ask if they had no Commodities to barter, and they replying they had Furs, we deſir'd to ſee them, and they fetched them imediately. There were White,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42107:30"/>Black, and Grey <hi>Foxes</hi> and ſome Sables, but not ſo well colored as are taken in <hi>Borenday, Samoieſſia,</hi> and <hi>Syberia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Commodity fitting us well, we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed our Tobacco for them and pleas'd them no leſs, having concluded our bargain and all things mutually delivered, we fell a drinking helter skelter together in which debauch we found they were not ſo ſavage as ſome others we had ſeen, though very rude in their converſation, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch things in our Company, as Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility will not ſuffer me to mention.</p>
               <p>It growing late, and we deſirous to paſs on in reſpect we had certain Rolls of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco, and ſome cloth remaining, we caus'd him to deſire our Hoſt to furniſh us with Sledges, and he having provided as many as we had occaſion for, we got in and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted about noon, and ran on till about ſix at night thorow very dangerous, and a man would have thought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſable places, without ſeeing either Horſe or Man, about half an hour after, going up an high Mountain, upon a little turning we percieved two Cabanes under the Rocks, which our Guide told us were the retreat of two <hi>Killoppes,</hi> who as ſoon as they ſaw us ran away with their Wives
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:42107:30"/>and Children. Three hours longer we marched before we diſcovered another, but then on the ſide of a little Hill we ſaw a fair Village built upon the Banck of a River, at which we arriv'd about eleven at night: and there our <hi>Elks</hi> were our Quarter-Maſters, and diſpos'd of us in the middle of the Town where we were well enough received, our Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord cauſing a good Fire to be made in the middle of the Room, bringing us for our ſupper, a proportion of Strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, dry'd Fiſh, and a piece of ſalted <hi>Elk,</hi> which was ſomething wonderful to us, in reſpect the Inhabitants all the way we had paſs'd thither, had not uſed any Salt, and there it was plentiful. He gave us Milk likewiſe and ſalt Butter very good, and doubtleſs it would have been much better had we had any Bread to have eat with it; but our ſtore was ſpent that very Morning, and we ſhould have been put to it, had we not had the good fortune to light there, our Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter muſt have made ſhift with dry Fiſh alone, not being able to endure any Salt, having ſupp'd, we betook our ſelves to our Bears-skins as uſually.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:42107:31"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> The Authors arrival at <hi>Kola,</hi> the ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Town, the manner of their buildings and other particulars.</head>
               <p>THe next day being the ſixteenth of <hi>May,</hi> there being no more Traffick in that Town, we paſs'd the River which was about the bredth of the <hi>Seine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being wafted over to a little Village on the other ſide of the Water, we went to the beſt houſe we could find, to ſee if they could furniſh us with Sledges to <hi>Kola,</hi> and being ſupplyed by them, we arrived there about noon.</p>
               <p>It is a ſmall Town, or large Country Village built among the Mountains, near a ſmall River diſtant about ten Leagues from the North-Sea. On the Eaſt ſide there are great Forreſts, on the Weſt, the Country of <hi>Mourm anskoimore,</hi> and on the South very high Mountains. Their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are built very low, for the moſt part of Wood covered over very beautifully with Fiſhes bones, and at top a kind of an open Lanthorn to let in the Light,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42107:31"/>the whole Town conſiſting but of one Street.</p>
               <p>The Inhabitants are generally (like moſt of the <hi>Muſcovites</hi>) <hi>Moroſe, diffident,</hi> and ſo extravagantly jealous, they ſhut up their Wives from the ſight and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Strangers. Our Landlord took all our cloth off our hands and gave us in lieu two <hi>Lynxes</hi> skins, ſpotted with Black and White like <hi>Leopards,</hi> three do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen of White <hi>Fox,</hi> half a doſen of <hi>Vie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefras,</hi> which we called <hi>Gloutons,</hi> and is a Creature not unlike a <hi>Badger,</hi> but with a longer and ruffer Fur, of a reddiſh black, with a tayl like a <hi>Foxes,</hi> beſides ſome few <hi>Ermins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having ſome few Ells of Linnen cloth remaining, more than he had Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to truck for, he bargained with us, to furniſh us with Proviſions for our journey back, and Sledges to the Town where we paſs'd the River, and in the mean time he treated us well according to the manner of that Country. After ſupper we betook our ſelves to our Bears skins, and took our quarters upon the Ground.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:42107:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> The Author leaves <hi>Kola</hi> in Order to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>Varanger;</hi> the pleaſant Funeral formalities among the <hi>Muſcovian Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe next morning (having told him we would be gon very early, our Hoſt had prepared our Proviſions accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to contract, which was bisket, a ſort of ſpice bread, <hi>Elks</hi> Fleſh baked with ſalt, with a barrel of <hi>Aqua-vitae,</hi> and our goods being made up, there came two of his Neighbours (hearing we had Tobacco left) to inquire if we would barter for any more skins; having told them we would, and they fetching them to us, they prov'd a dozen of <hi>Frmines,</hi> two dozen of White <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x,</hi> and four <hi>Lynxes,</hi> but not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo fair as what we had from our Landlord.</p>
               <p>The bargain being made, they delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kins, and we our Tobacco, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving only five Rolls both for our own uſe, and to diſcharge our expences in our return <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Varanger,</hi> as being a Commodity more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in that Country for Travellers, than
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:42107:32"/>Money, the <hi>Laplanders</hi> prizing an Inch of Tobacco more than a Crown in Silver; upon which conſideration the Kings of <hi>Denmark Sweden,</hi> and the great Duke of <hi>Muſcovy</hi> have laid great impoſts upon it in thoſe parts, and eſtabliſhed their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces upon the Frontiers to collect them.</p>
               <p>Our Trade being finiſhed, we were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to debauch in Strong-waters with our Merchants till two a clock after din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, at which time we deſired our Hoſt our Sledges might be got ready to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey us to <hi>Varanger,</hi> which he willingly granted, and having diſpos'd our goods into one of them, and our ſelves into the reſt, after a Styrrup Cup of <hi>Aqua-vitae,</hi> we took our leaves, and our <hi>Elks</hi> carried us (as if they alſo had had their doſe) with more expedition (in my judgment) than any before, in ſo much as about ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven we were got to the Village on the banck of the great River I mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, which we paſſed, and repair'd to our old quarters, where we were very kindly received by our Landlord, in hopes (as we conceived) he ſhould have a good lunchen of Tobacco to accommodate us again for our return. He gave us at firſt daſh a good diſh of ſtrong waters, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42107:33"/>then ask'd us if he ſhould provide us with Sledges, we told him not that night, for being weary we deſired to repoſe till next morning, there being never another Town within any reaſonable diſtance.</p>
               <p>Our Landlord having given us a large dram of the Bottle, he ask'd us if we would go along with him and ſee the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſolemnities for a Neighbour of his, who had dyed four hours before, which in curioſity we readily accepted.</p>
               <p>Being entred into the Houſe, we ſaw the Corps taken up by half a dozen of his principal Friends upon a large Bears skin, and laid upon a wooden Beer, the Corps was wrapped in linnen, with the Face uncovered, and both its hands: in one of them they had put a Purſe with a certain ſum of mony in it, to pay for his admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into Paradiſe; in the other it held a Paſtport or Ticket ſign'd by a Prieſt which was to be delivered to Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> to certify the honeſty of the man, and how proper he was to be received, by his ſide they had laid a barrel of ſtrong wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, with a proportion of Dri'd Fiſh and <hi>Elk</hi>-fleſh, for his repaſt by the way, in reſpect his journy was like to be long, after which they lighted ſeveral roots of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42107:33"/>
                  <hi>Firr</hi>-trees like ſo many Torches, and then fell a houling and crying with ſo many ſtrange poſtures and geſticulations, one would have ſworn they had been mad.</p>
               <p>All being ready, they took ſeveral turns about the Corps in Proceſſion, demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the reaſon of his Death; whither his Wife was not kind. Whether he wanted any thing; whether he was hungry, or a dry; whether he had had any diſaſter in his ſports; whether his clothes were out of repair, ſtill ſqualing and limping with ſeveral diſtortions of their bodies, and all the while a Prieſt ſtanding by, ſprinkling the Corps with Holy-water, and the Mourners doing the ſame.</p>
               <p>I ſhould have told that Saint <hi>Nicholas</hi> being in great Veneration among them as well as the <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> (are both <hi>Nicolai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> in their Opinions) they had plac'd an Image of him by the ſide of the Corps in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a Crucifix.</p>
               <p>This Saint <hi>Nicholas</hi> is not the Biſhop in the French Kalender whoſe Feſtival we keep, but one of the ſeaven Deacons men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Acts of the Apoſtles; they had carv'd him in the habit of a Pilgrim, his hood hanging looſe behind his head: a long looſe Gown with a large Gyrdle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42107:34"/>his Waſte, and his Staff in his hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> The work and imployment of thoſe <hi>Lapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> women, with other particulars of that place.</head>
               <p>TYr'd with the noiſe, and weary of the whole Ceremony, we withdrew to our Lodging, where we found our Landlady at Liberty, having forſaken the Hole where her Husband had diſpos'd her at our arrival.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as ſhe ſaw us, ſuppoſing her good Man was among us, ſhe was retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her Kennel; But our Guide and Interpreter letting her know he was ſafe at the Funeral, and not like to come home yet, ſhe pluck'd up a good heart, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured to ſtay.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing ſhe did ſhe ſtar'd round about her, and then fixing her eyes on each of us by turns (as ſhe had been picking a Mate) ſhe conſidered us all for ſome time, and as it ſeem'd not thinking a miſs of us, ſhe civilly ſate down, mumping, and bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42107:34"/>making many ſigns of her approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and friendſhip, and in heat of blood as a great Complement ſhewed us her work which was a Cap or Bonnet ſhe was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidering with Tynſel, one thread upon another very handſomly.</p>
               <p>The imployment of thoſe ſoeminine <hi>Laplanders,</hi> is nothing generally but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king clothes for themſelves, their hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands and Children, all of them embroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd with Tynſel at the bottom, which being ſofter then ordinary, they draw with their Teeth as fine and as long as any of our Wyer-drawers, and all with the prettyeſt grace imaginable; they are moſt of them handſome; well ſhap'd and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable enough were their nofes not a little Camus'd too much. The jealouſie of their husbands is terrible to them, and they dread the effects of their fury, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they are good natured, and would proſtitute upon occaſion without any great ſcruple: upon which conſideration the wary husbands deſire them to retire, when any ſtrangers come near.</p>
               <p>While our Hoſt was b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ed about the obſequie, of his Neighbour, and doing him his laſt honour, we drew out our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, and preſented our Landlady, the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:42107:35"/>good woman received them kindly, taſted them and liked them very well, eſpecially the ſpic'd-Cake, ſhe took two good ſoups of our Srong-water, and <hi>exit,</hi> being in a bodily fear her husband ſhould ſurpriſe her in our Company, which would have coſt her a cudgelling if ſhe had eſcaped with her brains.</p>
               <p>He returned at length, and we were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to take a Pipe, and another Dram with him; after which we went to Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and he gave us of his delicats, <hi>Elks</hi> Fleſh and Salt butter, which we eat with Bread, only our Guide having no fancy to any thing with Salt, contented himſelf with his dry'd Fiſh and a lunchen of <hi>Bears</hi> Fleſh our Landlord gave him, and he broil'd it upon the Coles.</p>
               <p>All the Houſes in this Town are like the reſt of that Country built of Wood, and covered with ſods of Earth, but ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned both without and within with the bones of Fiſhes, very curiouſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd.</p>
               <p>After ſupper we went to our lodging, which as formerly was upon <hi>Bear</hi>-skin ſpread upon the floor, where having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play'd our ſelves, we fell aſleep, and paſs'd the night in as much eaſe and ſecurity as any in our lives.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:42107:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> The Author in his return met a <hi>Muſcovite Laplander going a hunting.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE eighteenth of <hi>May</hi> very early in the morning, our Hoſt having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided us Sledges, and our Merchandiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put into one, we took up the reſt our ſelves, and departed; our <hi>Elks</hi> carrying us with no leſs ſwiftneſs, then thoſe our Hoſt had furniſhed us laſt from <hi>Kola,</hi> ſo that in about two hours time, we were advanced above ſix Leagues.</p>
               <p>Paſſing between two Hills, into a Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, we ſaw a <hi>Laplander</hi> going a hunting, He made towards us, ſliding along upon the Snow as faſt as we without ſinking in the leaſt. His Pattins were made of the Bark of a Tree, about ſeven foot and a half long, bending almoſt to a Semi-Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, but four fingers broad, flat at the bottom, and a hallow place where he put his Foot and tyed his Shooes to it, his Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit was <hi>Elks</hi> skin dreſt with the hair on. His Cap, Mittans, Jump, Breeches, and Boots all bordered with Tyncel, and ty'd about the waſt with a Gyrdle of the ſame
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42107:36"/>In one hand his Bow, in the other his Dart, with his Quiver of Arrows at his back, and his beloved Catt at his heels.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> The Authors return to <hi>Varanger;</hi> the dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the <hi>Laplanders</hi> in throwing their Darts, ſhooting with their Bows, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther particulars.</head>
               <p>OUr <hi>Laponian</hi> Huntsman having kept with us about half a League, he left us at the foot of a Hill, we marching one way, and he another, by the expedition we made, we arrived at <hi>Varanger</hi> about nine at night, having taken the ſame way, and met the ſame conveniences we found as we went, without any injury or acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent whatever.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Laplanders</hi> (though very poor; Brutiſh and for the moſt part Sorcerers) are very faithful notwithſtanding, not at all given to nimming or ſtealing which is the principle of their virtues; they are dextrous in throwing their Darts, they will hit a Crown piece thirty Paces off, and ſtick a man thorow and thorow, with
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:42107:36"/>ſuch ſtrength and activity do they fling them, and with their Bow they will hit any Beaſt in what part ſoever they pleaſe.</p>
               <p>They have no great Maw to the Wars, nor natural affection to the other World, inſomuch as when the Kings of <hi>Denmark, Sweden,</hi> or the great Duke of <hi>Muſcovy</hi> want men, and make their Levies in theſe Countries they betake themſelves to the Woods, believing the wild Beaſts leſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>human then mankind to it ſelf.</p>
               <p>They have Foul, as <hi>Geeſe, Hens, Ducks,</hi> and others, which they feed not with <hi>Juniper</hi> Corn, but with another Grain of which they make their Beer, but of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more plenty than Fiſh.</p>
               <p>The moſt part of the Wild-Beaſts in <hi>Lapouia</hi> are white, as <hi>Woolfs, Foxes, Hares,</hi> and others, even their <hi>Crowes</hi> are white, to as high a degree as our <hi>Swans</hi> without any black about them but their Beak and their Feet.</p>
               <p>The Fiſh which they dry to ſerve them inſtead of Bread are large and of the length of betwixt two and three <hi>French</hi> Eeles, without any Bones beſides that of the Back, which the Phyſicians call <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na dorſi,</hi> the marrow of which they call <hi>Raff,</hi> and is well taſted, ſubſtantial and thick.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:42107:37"/>
               <p>The Fiſh they boyl, and eat by it ſelf, are of all other ſorts; the diſhes and Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels they uſe are of Copper or Wood, and and though they hate ſalt, and uſe none of it at all, yet they boyl all their meat in Sea-water, and it goes down very well.</p>
               <p>Their Dogs are ſmall, the biggeſt not above a foot long, and a ſpan high, their hair the length of a Finger, of a darkiſh Red, ſhagged and ſtaring like Briſſels, their Ears are exactly like a <hi>Woolfs,</hi> their head and muzzel like a Bats, which they hunt like Cats, and eat them when they have done, upon which account, they are in high eſteem among the <hi>Laplanders,</hi> though they be ill-favoured, dull, and their Tayls curling like a Pig.</p>
               <p>They have a kind of wild-Foul among them of a Pearl-colour'd grey, about the bigneſs of a <hi>Goſhawk;</hi> their eyes red and ſparkling, their head like a Cat, their beak like an Eagle, their Feet and Talons like the ſame, with which they ſeize and ſecure their prey, both Hares and other Game.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:42107:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> The Authorr ſayling out of the Sea of <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranger,</hi> the continuation of his Voyage and other particulars.</head>
               <p>THe day we arrived at <hi>Varanger</hi> our Maſter began to caulk, and the next had finiſhed, and our Ship being once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in good order, he caus'd our goods to be be put on Board. While we ſtaid, we treated the Inhabitants with Strong-Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Tobacco, leſt they ſhould obſtruct our departure, and hinder our Wind; but they were ſo far from that, that about five days after being the 26. of <hi>May</hi> (as if in recompence of our kindneſs) there aroſe ſo pleaſant and convenient a Wind to carry us out of that Sea, we took the advantage, weighed, and were under Sail about ſeaven at night.</p>
               <p>The wind increaſing, to avoid the Rocks in the middle of the paſſage into the main Ocean, we came to Anchor near the Shore over againſt the Iſle of <hi>Wardbus,</hi> from whence the Commiſs of the Caſtle perceiving us, and knowing who we were, came with his Shallop on Board us, and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:42107:38"/>having treated him well and civily, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome hours he took his leave and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.</p>
               <p>The next day being the 27. the Sun ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing with his rays about one a Clock in the night, we weighed again, ſtanding directly for the main Sea, which by the aſſiſtance of a freſh Gale, we might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably gain, ſteering <hi>N. N. E.</hi> with full Sail, and as much pleaſure as we could wiſh.</p>
               <p>We had not Sailed three times four and twenty hours, before the night for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook us quite, the Sun continuing always in our ſight either behind, before, or on one ſide of us.</p>
               <p>The laſt of <hi>May</hi> we diſcovered the Mountains called <hi>Spite Bergen,</hi> but being obſtructed with a North wind which blew very hard, not able to keep the Sea, we were forced to leave them to the <hi>N. N. E.</hi> and ſteer our courſe <hi>E. S. E.</hi> to make the ſhore if we could, and ſecure our ſelves there.</p>
               <p>For three days and nights we were in no little danger, much incommoded by the Ice, which being broken and ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the agitation of the Tempeſt, came upon us in great pieces, daſhing with that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:42107:38"/>violence againſt the Poup and ſides of our Ship, we looked every moment to have been broken in pieces.</p>
               <p>The fourth of <hi>June,</hi> at due Eaſt, we deſcryed high Mountains, and directed our courſe to them, to put our ſelves if poſſible under the protection of a certain Promontory which we diſcovered. But the wind blowing hard again at the North we were glad to ſteer towards the Coaſts of <hi>Boranday</hi> which we reached in few hours, and put into a Bay which we found there, very convenient to ſhelter us againſt the winds, and furniſhing us with twelve or thirteen fathom water.</p>
               <p>We were at Anchor no ſooner, but we ſaw two Ships within Muſquet-ſhot from us, and we perceived them to be ours, which had left us in the ſtorm on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſide the North-Cape, and we ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed had been caſt away: we were very glad we were miſtaken, and gave them the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of our arrival by ſhooting off three Guns, and hanging out our great Flag upon our Poup.</p>
               <p>To expreſs the joy they alſo conceived at the news of our welfare, they belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us drown'd in the tempeſt that part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us, they not only re-ſaulted us with
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:42107:39"/>their Cannon, but hung out all their Flags and decorations, and we the like, deſiring on both ſides to put out our Shallops and come on board one another, but the wind was too high, and we were forced to ſtay till it abated, which it did about four and twenty hours after.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIV.</hi> The meeting of the Daniſh Ships which came out of <hi>Denmark</hi> with the Author, their ſeparation by Storm, and an account of their adventures.</head>
               <p>THE great deſire our friends in thoſe two Ships had to know whether that Tempeſt had carried us when we were parted, cauſed them each of them to put out their Long-Boat to come aboard us, which they did with great ſatisfaction on all ſides: they gave us over for loſt, as we had done them, and concluded we ſhould never have met again.</p>
               <p>They gave us a relation how they were driven by the Wind upon the Coaſts of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horsky</hi> not far from an Iſland, but not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to come to an Anchor by reaſon
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:42107:39"/>of the Rocks which they diſcovered in their ſounding coming once within two Fathom and a half water, they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſodainly to vere, and (by the favour of an <hi>E. N. E.</hi> wind) to keep the Sea as well as they could, which they performed with no little trouble, till at length after three days contentions with the Seas and the weather they came into the Bay where we found them, under the Promontories of <hi>Boranday,</hi> about eight or nine Leagues from an Iſland called <hi>Kildomovia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We gave them on our ſide an account of the dangers we had run, how we were forced into the Sea of <hi>Varanger,</hi> and driven to an Anchor before the Town, to refit our Veſſel, and put it into a condition to Sail having ſcaped ſinking ſo narrowly: we told them likewiſe our tranſaction in the <hi>Daniſh, Swediſh,</hi> and <hi>Muſcovite Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the trade we had had, and all our other adventures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:42107:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> The reſolution the <hi>Danes</hi> took to Trade in <hi>Boranday,</hi> and the Authors going along <hi>with them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE ſtory of our ſucceſs made them take up a reſolution to go thither, and ſee if they could find any that would traffick with them.</p>
               <p>In order to this we held a Counſel, in which it was unanimouſly conluded that one of our Maſters, one Commiſs, two ſub-Commiſſes or Factors who underſtood the Northern and <hi>Ruſſian</hi> Languages, with twenty Seamen and my ſelf, all well Arm'd and provided for ſeveral days, ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the deſign.</p>
               <p>All things being decreed, and every thing ready they furniſhed us with two Shallops to put us on Shore, which being done, we got on the top of a little hill to ſee if we could diſcover any houſes. Find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none, we marched towards a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain about half a League off from the top of which we diſcovered ſome two or three flight-ſhot from us about 5 or 6 perſons among the Buſhes coming towards us, but
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:42107:40"/>as ſoon as they perceived us away they ran in ſuch halt we quickly loſt the ſight of them.</p>
               <p>However we followed their track ſo well obſerving which way they pointed their flight, that about two hours after going down the Mountain, we ſaw in a Vally ſome few houſes, and making to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them we found thirty or forty per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons armed with Arrows and Darts, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to receive and ſight us upon occaſion, ſuppoſing by the greatneſs of our Troop, we were come to do them ſome injury, upon which we ſtopped our Career, and called a Counſel whether we had beſt go back or advance, ſeeing the Inbabitans were bold and couragious and we in no neceſſity to provoke them.</p>
               <p>One of the Sub-commiſſes offered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to go towards them alone, to let them know we were Friends and Merchants, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring nothing but Trade with them, if if they had any thing convenient for us, or we for them.</p>
               <p>The Propoſition being generally appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, he advanced towards the Natives with two Rowls of Tobacco, and a little Barrel of <hi>Aqua vitae.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:42107:41"/>
               <p>Being got within diſtance of hearing, and being heard, one of them called out to him in the <hi>Moſcovian</hi> Language to know what we were, &amp; what was our deſign, our Envoy told him we were Merchants, Friends, and that our deſire was to have their Friendſhip, and be admitted to Trade with them, if they liked our Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities. Being ſatisfied with the Anſwer, he ſatisfied the reſt, and made a ſign to us to come on, and we did as they deſired.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:42107:41"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> The Statue, Habit, Buildings, and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of living of the <hi>Barandians,</hi> with other particulars.</head>
               <p>WHen we came near them, I was amazed to find them much leſs than the <hi>Laponians,</hi> their Eyes of the ſame bigneſs, deepneſs, and colour, that which we call the White, being of a Reddiſh Yealow, their Face flat and broad, their Head exceeding large, their Noſes Camus, their Complexion as ſwarthy as poſſible, and their Legs like ſo many Mill-poſts.</p>
               <p>The Cloaths were firſt a pair of Breeches as ſtraight as could be made, then a a Waſtcoat or Jump which came down to their Knees, their Stockins and Caps of white Bears skin with the Hair outward, and their Shooes of the Bark of Trees.</p>
               <p>Their Houſes are all built and covered with Fiſh Bones, very low their faſhion Oval, without any light but what comes in at the door, which is not much unlike the mouth of an Oven.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:42107:42"/>
               <p>Theſe people live wholly by Fiſhing and Hunting, they cat all their meat with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any thing of Salt; their dry Fiſh ſerves them for Bread, their Drink is fair Water, in which they Infuſe their Juniper-berries, which gives it a ſharpiſh but plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Tincture, eſpecially if drank in a Cup of the ſame Wood.</p>
               <p>The Women are as ill-favoured as the Men, their Habits and Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame, going in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with their Husbands a Fiſhing and Hunting. In ſhort they have no Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and little more Humanity than Beaſts.</p>
               <p>We ſwapt with them all the Tobacco and Strong Waters we had carryed with us for our Proviſion, for Woolf, Foxes, and ſome few Ermine Skins they delivered to us. Having more skins thy were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to barter, we deſired them to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to our Ships, and they ſhould have what they pleaſed, which they accepted, and having fetched what they had, they all of them marched along to the Sea ſide; they were no ſooner in ſight of our Veſſel, but they admired it exceedingly. We gave the ſign to have Boats ſent us, and immediately each of our Ships ſent two:
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:42107:42"/>the Commiſs. I, and the Sub-Commiſs. (who ventured to the malone and gave us the opportunity of being acquainted with them) went all three of us into one of them, taking him that invited our Sub-Commiſs. to a Treaty, and another <hi>Boran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> with us who ſpoke the <hi>Muſcovian</hi> Language very well, all the reſt remained on Shore.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVII.</hi> The entertainment the <hi>Danes</hi> gave them on Board, and the Authors voyage into <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randay.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEing come a Board, our Maſter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing acquainted with the ſtory of our adventures, and how ſavage and bruitiſh the <hi>Borandians</hi> were, to ſweeten and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jole them, that they might be ſerviceable to us, he gave each of them a peice of Tobacco about the length of a finger, and a Cup of ſtrong waters, which they took extream kindly, and having ſome skins fell to barterring immediately. We ask'd them whither if we went higher up into the Country, we might expect any traffick
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:42107:43"/>they reply'd yes we might, but all their Commodities would be nothing but Furs, and we telling them we deſired no more, they aſſured us we ſhould find e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of that nature which would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed for our Tobacco and Strong-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that if we would ſatisfy them for their pains, they would conduct us as far as <hi>Siberia:</hi> we agreed to give each of them two Rolls of Tobacco, and four pints of Strong-water, to conduct us back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and forward, promiſing ſomething ſupernumerary, if by their means our jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney turned to any conſiderable account; in ſhort all things were agreed, only they preſſed that we ſhould pay for the Sledges and <hi>Elks</hi> we uſed by the way out of our own purſes beſides, which being but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable the Maſter conſented.</p>
               <p>The bargain being made, and a cup of wine given to each of them to confirm it, we put them again into our Shallop, and ſet them a Shore, they had ingaged to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare things withal ſpeed for our journey, and they were as good as their word: for no ſooner were they on land, but away they ran about their buſineſs, and in eight hours time returned with Sledges, <hi>Elks</hi> and every thing convenient for our jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:42107:43"/>
               <p>Whilſt we were in this manner treating thoſe on Board, the other Ships cauſed ſtrong Water and Tobacco to be ſent on Shore to barter with thoſe which remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, expecting the return of their Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rades, not being to be perſwaded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into our Shallops, for fear they ſhould never come back again: which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged all our Maſters by way of inſinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to cauſe certain ſmall Barrels of <hi>Aqua-Vitae</hi> to be carried to them and drank out among them: which they received ſo thankfully, as in token of their gratitude, they deſired our Company to go along with them, and take ſuch entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as their Houſes and conditions would afford, but this Offer was made on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie by ſignes, for no body underſtood their Language.</p>
               <p>Our two <hi>Borandiras</hi> being come back with Sledges and as many <hi>Elks,</hi> we ask'd why they brought no more, and their anſwer was, there were no more to be gotten. Obſerving them larger then in <hi>Laponia,</hi> we inquired if they were ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and were told they were. That the <hi>Laponia Elk</hi> could draw but one man, and theſe would draw two, and accordingly each of the Sledges were made to carry
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:42107:44"/>two: which being reported to our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, it was in Counſel reſolv'd that our Commiſs. the two Sub-Commiſſioners, (that ſpake <hi>Ruſs</hi> very well) my ſelf, and a Sea man out of each Ship ſhould go along with theſe two <hi>Borandians</hi> and Trade. Upon this deſigne they loaded one of the <hi>Elks</hi> with Tobacco, Strong water, Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and ſome Gold, in all to a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble value. I was placed with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs. one of us at one end, the other at the other, with our Faces upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, one of the Sub's was placed in the ſame manner with one of the <hi>Borandians,</hi> the other with the other, two of our Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men together, and the third being alone, had the reſt of the Room filled up with Barrels of Strong-water, and Tobacco, and in this poſture we ſet out.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Elks</hi> carryed us with as much (if not more ſpeed) then thoſe in <hi>Lapland,</hi> ſo that for eight hours together we were hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried over Mountains, thorow Fields, and Vallies without ſeeing either Perſon or Houſe; at length coming near a great wood of Firr-Trees, we could perceive five or ſix about an hundred Paces from us, near one of which we baited our <hi>Elks</hi> upon the Moſs, and refreſhed our ſelves
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:42107:44"/>with Biſcuit and ſalt meat, and our <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randians</hi> with dryed Fiſh dipped in Oyl, which was provided on purpoſe for them, they not enduring our Bread or Salt. Our Drink was out of a Spring hard by, after which we took a dram of the bottle and away to our Sledges again, continuing our courſe three hours longer, and then at the bottom of a great Mountain we could perceive ſeveral Houſes hard by one another, where it was deſign'd we ſhould repoſe that night. When we were got to them, we found them ſo little we were forc'd to divide and quarter in two ſeveral Cabanes, which we did very contentedly, whilſt our Guids unharneſſed our <hi>Elks</hi> and turn'd them to Graſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:42107:45"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> The conſequence of the Authors voyage into <hi>Boranday,</hi> and ſome particulars of the Natives.</head>
               <p>HAving repos'd for ſix or ſeaven hours upon Pallats of <hi>Bears</hi>-skins, which our Landlord had ſpread upon the ground for our entertainment, we got up and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired if they had nothing to truck, upon which they produced ſeveral <hi>Woolf</hi>-skins, white <hi>Foxes,</hi> two dozen of <hi>Ermins,</hi> about three hundred <hi>Squirrels,</hi> and ſeaven pair of <hi>Sables.</hi> They would not meddle with our Tobacco, as not being ſo ſweet tooth'd and well bred as their Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men upon the coaſt, living only upon hunting. In Summer their diet is freſh meat boyl'd or broyl'd upon the Coals. In Winter nothing but dry meat, which they provide in the Summer by drying it in the Sun upon a Wheel or on the top of their Houſes, which are built very low, cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over with branches of trees and Turfs of Earth, without any light but what comes in at the door, which as aforeſaid is like the mouth of an Oven.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:42107:45"/>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Borandines</hi> (as our Guides told us) change their Quarters as often as the <hi>Killopes,</hi> they live brutiſhly without any Religion, and are more ſtupid then any we met with, They are as ill-ſhaped as their Neighbours. Their Shoos are of the Bark of a Tree, their Stockings, Breeches, Capps and Coats (which come down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the Calf of their Leggs, and girt about with a Girdle about four fingers broad) are all of white <hi>Bears</hi>-skin with the hair outward. The Women are not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable from the Men but by their Hair, which is braided and hangs down upon their Shoulders. They are as nimble and skilful at hunting as their Husbands. Their Arms are only a pointed Stick of a certain hard-wood which pierces any thing, a wooden Bow, the String made of the Rinde of a Tree, a Quiver of Arrowes at their Backs, and a Stone that cuts like a Raſour at their Gyrdle.</p>
               <p>Our Trade being finiſhed, our Guides having provided our Sledges, and each of us taken a good draught of Strong-water, we mounted and away running on nine or ten hours together before we ſaw man or houſe, at length we perceived three or four Houſes, and our Guides perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:42107:46"/>our <hi>Elks</hi> to make to them, where though we found no body, we made bold to repoſe our ſelves, and refreſh our Cattel, whoſe Diet was nothing but Moſs, and at that place they kept a plentiful Table.</p>
               <p>We eat and drank ſuch as we had, and were as merry as Beggars, when we had done (after three hours relax) we mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again, and continued our Voyage as induſtriouſly as we could.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> The Author meets a <hi>Borandine</hi>-Lord with two of his Servants coming from Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with a deſcription of their Clothes.</head>
               <p>AFter fifteen hours travel (without other intermiſſion then once to feed our <hi>Elkrs</hi> and repoſe our ſelves) having ſeen neither Houſe nor Man in all that time, we perceived three Huntſ-men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, and made up to them; one of them was habited <hi>a la Muſcovite</hi> in a long Robe down to his Heels, with a Girdle about his Waſt four fingers broad of <hi>Woolfs</hi> skin the hair outward, it was as white as Snow, and at the point as black as Jett;
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:42107:46"/>he had a Bonn et round (like a Seamans) of Black <hi>Fox,</hi> his Breeches and Stockings of <hi>Elks</hi>-skin, and his Shoos of Fiſh-skin, like the Inhabitants in <hi>Varanger.</hi> The other had the Veſts of the ſame faſhion of White <hi>Bears,</hi> the hair outward, and their Shoos of Fiſh skin: they had each of them a dozen of <hi>Bears</hi>-skins, <hi>Woolfs</hi>-skins, White <hi>Fox,</hi> ſome <hi>Ermins,</hi> and very fair <hi>Sable,</hi> as I have ſeen; He that was in the White <hi>Woolfs</hi>-skin, carryed nothing but a dozen of White <hi>Crowes,</hi> and ſeaven <hi>Sables</hi> hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at his Girdle.</p>
               <p>Being got up with them, one of our Guides ſtopped on a ſuddain to ſpeak with the chief of them, and preſently alight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from his Sledge, put him in his place with one of our Sub-Commiſſioners, at which my Commiſs. and I were very much ſurpriſed. In this manner he went along with us above an hour and we could ſee never a Houſe; at length from the top of an high Mountain we could ſee the Sea on our left hand, and at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom ſeveral Houſes, ſtanding near one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like a ſmall Town. Our <hi>Elks</hi> carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us to them directly, and we alighted to repoſe in the Houſe of that Lord whom our Guide put into his place; we knew
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:42107:47"/>him to be a perſon of more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry authority, by the officiouſneſs of the Inhabitants, who ran immediately to our aſſiſtance, and helped us out of our Sled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges with all the readineſs imaginable. The Towns name was <hi>Vizzora.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord ſwopt with us for our Tobac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co and Strong-waters, and gave us in lieu all the skins he had got except his <hi>Bears</hi>-skins which we would not meddle with, and his <hi>Sables</hi> which he durſt not part with, they being prohibited by the great Duke of <hi>Muſcovy</hi> (whom they call the <hi>Czar</hi>) who preſerves them for himſelf, no body daring to ſell any of them in all his Dominions, but by licenſe from himſelf, or his Commiſſioners (reſident in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where he has Magazines) under great corporal penalties, ſo that if they ſell any at any time, 'tis with great caution and privacy, and they who buy them are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to keep it cloſe, for if the Commiſs. or Governor of thoſe places where all Merchandize is ſearched, do find any <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> which have not been ſold by the Duke himſelf, his Officers, or his Licence, not only they but all the goods that Merchant hath are confiscate without redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:42107:47"/>The <hi>Borandine</hi> Lord, having diſpatched his own buſineſs, and trucked all he had him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, knowing we had a mind to more, he ſent two of his Servants quite thorow the Town to give notice that if they deſired to part with what skins they had, if they carryed them to us, we would give them Tobacco and Strong-water for them, and that their Maſter had dealt with us for all he had. Being glad of the opportunity, they repaired all of them with their Furs, and we bought what we thought fit.</p>
               <p>Having no leſs than fifteen hundred skins of all ſorts, we inquired of our Landlord if he could not provide us a Boat to ſend one of our Seamen with our Trade to our Ships; he told us he could, and cauſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one to be got ready, it was in the faſhion of a <hi>Gondelo,</hi> broad in the middle, and pointed at both ends, all of wood, without either Iron-work or nail, in the midſt it had a Maſt of <hi>Firr</hi> with a great four ſquare ſail (faſtned to it) of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen made of the Rinde of a Tree, and Tynſeld very handſomly: the Cordage was made of the Rinde of Trees alſo, there were two Anchors belonged to it, made of a heavy kind of wood which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried it preſently to the bottom, and Cables
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:42107:48"/>of the ſame with their Cordage.</p>
               <p>Having appointed us two men to go a long with our Sea-Man, and ſeeing them ready to depart, he carryed us a ſide, and ſhew'd us thirty pair of <hi>Sables,</hi> which we bought of him for ready mony, at a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty good rate, and were not at all ſorry for it; had not we had the luck to have borrowed his Boat, and he ſeen it immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to be diſpatched to our Veſſels where he knew no Searcher could come, we could not have tempted him to part with them, as knowing very well if he were diſcovered he ſhould not only be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to corporal puniſhment, but he and his generation ſent Slaves into <hi>Sibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> where they might remain long enough before they returned.</p>
               <p>Our Scaman and his two <hi>Borandine</hi> Camerades being departed, our Commiſs. and the two Sub-Commiſſes. fell in a drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him and our Guides. I and the two other Seamen took that opportunity and went to view the Town. We admired it exceedingly being ſcituate betwixt two Mountains about a league high either of them. The Houſes were built of Fiſh-bones very artificially, the Roofs of the ſame, but ſtopped in ſome places with Moſs, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:42107:48"/>with Flags of Earth, ſo cloſe no wind could come in but at the doors (which are like the mouth of a Furnace) and a top the Houſe where there is a hole or window left for light to come in. We ſaw ſeveral of their Women and Children at work, ſome of them making of Netts (of the Rinde of Trees) for their Fiſhing, others Sails for their Boats, of a kind of a ſine Mat, others Axes, Swords, pointed Darts, and Arrows of the Bones of Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. Others making of Clothes of <hi>Bears</hi>-skin ſowed together with thread made of the Rinde of Trees, with needles of the ſmall bones of Fiſh, they were all of them ugly, little, flat nos'd, and ſwarthy as Devils.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:42107:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXX.</hi> The Authors departure from <hi>Vitzora to go</hi> to <hi>Potzora,</hi> and his <hi>Traffick there.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEing returned to our Company, our Commiſs. and Sub-Commiſs. upon Conſultation reſolved to ſend back one of our Guides with the Sledges and <hi>Elks,</hi> and to take the convenience of the water to paſs to <hi>Potzora,</hi> which was accordingly performed. Our Landlord and two of his Servants in complement went along with us, and Coaſting along the Shore by the favour of a Weſterly wind, in fifteen hours we made <hi>Potzora,</hi> which is a ſmall Town upon a little Sea called by that name; we repaired immediately to the Caſtle to pay our reſpects to the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, who in truth is no more than a Factor or Agent for the great <hi>Czar;</hi> all the Governors belonging to that Duke being no other in thoſe parts. There be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing few of the nobility in <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> which in my judgment is the reaſon they are ſo rude and unpolliſhed, a thing inconſiſtent with the education of the nobles.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:42107:49"/>
               <p>The Governor was a <hi>Muſcovite,</hi> his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit cloth betwixt a Violet colour and a Red, he treated us indifferent well, with Hydromets of an excellent ſort (not much unlike our Spaniſh wine) ſtrong waters and ſpice-bread. Having the charge of the <hi>Czars Magazines</hi> of <hi>Sables</hi> we ask'd him if he would deal with us for any, he told us he would, and demanding what we would buy, we replyed all he had, if we might have them at reaſonable Rates; whereupon he carryed us to his Ware-Houſe, and ſhew'd us five <hi>Zimmers</hi> (which are fifty pair) of which two <hi>Zimmers</hi> were the beſt I ever ſaw, being naturally black as Jet, for which parcel we paid him 500 Ducates, which amount to three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>French</hi> Livers, and for the other four hundred Ducates, which was as much as eight hundred <hi>French</hi>-Crowns.</p>
               <p>Having paid him for what we had, and ſeen them marked with the Grand Dukes Seal, he would needs give us a treat, to which purpoſe he diſpatched two Shallops to get freſh-Fiſh, he killed a young <hi>Elk,</hi> and with ſome Foul his Servants had got abroad, he made us a magnificent Feaſt, both of Fleſh, Fiſh, and <hi>Muſcovian</hi> Biſcuit. We ſat eight hours compleat at the Table,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:42107:50"/>and by that time the fumes of the Hydro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met and Strong-Waters we had drank being got up into our Heads, we were glad to draw off to our <hi>Bears</hi>-skins which were all the beds we could get.</p>
               <p>Having ſlept ſix or ſeven hours, we got up, drank a Cup of Strong-Waters, and then went into the Town with a little Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer the Governor ſent along with us, who carried us where we found two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Squirrel</hi>-Skins, four dozen of <hi>Ermins,</hi> five hundred <hi>Fox</hi>-skins (the moſt of them as white as Snow, and the reſt black) <hi>ſix-Woolfs</hi>-skins, two hundred <hi>Martins,</hi> of a kind of an Aſh-coloured-Grey, which coſt us (all of them) four hundred Ducates in Copper Mony (which troubled us to carry about) after which we returned to the Catle with our Merchandiſe, and packed them up in bails of Mats made of the Rinde of a Tree.</p>
               <p>Having packed up our goods in this manner, we concluded to ſend one of our Sub-Commiſſes with them to our Ships, to which end we intreated our Hoſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor to accommodate us with a Boat to convey them, which he readily granted, and two hours after our Officer departed with three <hi>Borandines</hi> the Governor lent
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:42107:50"/>us, he having firſt ingaged they ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them ſafe in our Ships, and that pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ten Ducats, and giving the men that carried them ſome ſmall proportion of Tobacco, he would ſatisfie the reſt at their return.</p>
               <p>Our Sub-Commiſs. and his Camrades being gone, we fell a drinking pell-mell with our brace of Governors, and the Governor of <hi>Vitzora</hi> took of his Cups ſo liberally, I could ſcarce imagine where he diſpoſed them. This debauch continued full four hours and then we went to our reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:42107:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXI.</hi> The Authors departure from <hi>Potzora</hi> to go into <hi>Siberia</hi> his meeting with five perſons ſent thither into exile by the grand Duke, the miſeries they endured, and his arrival at <hi>Papinogorod.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS ſoon as we were up in the morning, our Commiſs. intreated the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>Potzora</hi> to furniſh us with Sledges for our paſſage into <hi>Siberia:</hi> He provided us ſeven, one for our Commiſs. one for our Sub-Commiſs. one for me, two for our two Marriners, one for our Guide and the other for our Tobacco, Strong-waters, and the proviſions he gave us for our journey, but our mony the Commiſs. took along with himſelf.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Elks</hi> being harneſſed, and put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sledges, he cauſed another to be got ready for another Guide he ſent along with us to the place where we were to change our <hi>Elks,</hi> and deliver his; for all which we contracted to give him four Ducates, but before we parted, each of usdrank five or ſix cups of Strong-waters to take our leaves, and having given the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:42107:51"/>Governor of <hi>Potzora</hi> and <hi>Vitzora</hi> thanks for their Civilities, we departed follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the River thorow very dangerous pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, without keeping any beaten Road four hours together without the ſight of any living Creature but four white <hi>Bears</hi> the vaſteſt that ever were ſeen, which (as ſoon as they diſcovered us) ran away as hard as they could; about two hours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, before we were aware, we were got to ſeven or eight houſes, but no body to be found in them, the inhabitants being all of them gon a hunting.</p>
               <p>We alighted from our Sledges, and went in to refreſh, and in the mean time five or ſix Men and Women with their Children returned from the Chaſe (which had been for tunate that day. They brought along with them ſix <hi>Bears</hi>-skins, four <hi>Woolfs,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen white <hi>Foxes,</hi> a couple of <hi>Ermins,</hi> and eight <hi>Sables.</hi> They were much ſurpriſed to find us in their Quarters and had beta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them to their heels, had not the Guide lent us by the Governor of <hi>Potzora</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken and aſſured them we were friends and Merchants paſſing to <hi>Papinogorod,</hi> and that we would be their Chapmen for all the skins they had, upon his perſwaſion they came back, but gaping and ſtaring
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:42107:52"/>in the greateſt admiration in the World' both in reſpect of our habits (which were ſtrange to them) our ſhape and our lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, of which they underſtood not one word no more than we did of theirs; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever by the help of our Interpreter we made a ſhift to barter with them, and they furniſhed us with <hi>Elks</hi> to carry us to the Mouth of <hi>Papinogorod</hi> River.</p>
               <p>Being got out of the River of <hi>Potzora</hi> about two hours, and following that which carried us to <hi>Papinogorod,</hi> we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcri'd coming out of a great Wood five men clad in <hi>Bears</hi> skin after the faſhion of <hi>Muſcovia,</hi> each of them with a Gun up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Shoulder, his Bags by his ſide, and a ſhort Sword in his hand like one of our Huntsmen, making toward us, we cauſed our Sledges to ſtop, and our Guide to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what people they were. One of them diſcerning we were ſtrangers, ſaluted us in Dutch, gave us the time of the day, and wiſhed himſelf at as much liberty as we. Our Commiſs. (who was born in the lower <hi>Saxony</hi>) hearing him ſpeak Dutch, demanded his Country, to which the perſon replied, and our Commiſs. find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him of his aquaintance, alighted from his Sledge, took him in his Arms, and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:42107:52"/>having embraced, deſired the occaſion of his being there. The perſon replyed he was baniſhed thither by the great Duke for hunting of <hi>Sables,</hi> which is a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as ordinary in that Country, as ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Gallies in <hi>France,</hi> ſome being baniſhed for ten years, ſome for ſix, others for three, more or leſs according to the quality of their offence, and after their time is expired, they have their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and are free.</p>
               <p>Their acquaintance, and my own curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity fetched me alſo out of my Sledge, and no ſooner had I ſet foot upon the ground, but another of them came and embraced me, and then in the <hi>French</hi> Tongue with a ſigh, asked me from whence I came, and whither I deſigned. I was much ſurpriſed, not knowing him in the leaſt by reaſon of his habit, his great beard, his bald pate, and the lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his body, being nothing but skin and bone; he perceived I was at a loſs, and told me he was a Gentleman of <hi>Lorain</hi> Colonel of a Regiment of Horſe for the Duke of <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> had ſeen and treated me often at his houſe in <hi>Stockholm,</hi> and had endeavoured to have perſwaded me along with him to <hi>Moſco.</hi> The fair equipage in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:42107:53"/>which I had ſeen him, the reſpect every body ſhewed him for his eſtate, his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in the Army, and the bravery of his perſon, conſidered with the pittiful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition he was then in, forced tears from my eyes in ſpight of my teeth: I embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him again, and deſiring to know the reaſon of his diſgrace, he told me it was for a ſuſpicion the great Duke had concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of his fidelity, and for that reaſon had baniſhed him into <hi>Siberia.</hi> He told me he had, and was yet to run thorow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible dangers and miſeriers (inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to men in his condition) not only of hunger, and ſeverity of the weather, but in perpetual Hunting expoſed to the capacity of Wild-Beaſts, which for want of food did many times attack thoſe which Hunted them, for which reaſon they carried thoſe Arms, to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and that beſides all theſe miſeries if they did not take their appointed num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Sables,</hi> whether it was negligence or not, they were never examined, but were ſure of ſo many laſhes upon their bare Fleſh with certain Girdles made of a thick and tuff skin, which were in tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to bear. Our Commiſs. his friend told him the ſame, and the reſt (ſpeaking all of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:42107:53"/>them good <hi>French</hi> &amp; <hi>Dutch</hi>) confirmed it to be true; one of them had been a grand Commiſs. to the great Duke, another a Lievtenant General of all them perſons of quality, who after a ſad relation of their ſorrows, aſſured us unanimouſly that if it pleaſed God they outlived the time of their ſentence, and were once again at liberty, they would never conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in any Country under the power of the Grand Duke. To comfort them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their calamities, we took out our Proviſions, ſate down altogether upon the ground, and treated them as we could. We told them how glad we would be if we could be any ways inſtrumental to their inlargment; for which they gave us thanks, but told us it was impoſſible, in reſpect they were known to all the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors in thoſe parts thorow which of neceſſity we muſt paſs, and that if they were taken with us they ſhould be ſure to die by the moſt exquiſite tortures, and we unavoidably looſe our lives into the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. This they remonſtrated vvith ſo much frankneſs and ingenuity, it redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the grief vve had already conceived finding our ſelves unable to relieve them in ſo miſerable an exigence. Having ſtaid
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:42107:54"/>and converſed with them full four hours, we thought it time to take our leaves, and having preſented each of them with half a pound of Tobacco, after they had drank well of our Strong-Waters, and eaten of the Biſcuit and ſpiced Bread we brought from <hi>Potzora,</hi> and ſome of our ſalt meat, we bad them farewell, beſeeching God Almighty to give them power to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all they were to encounter, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to ſee them again in their former ſplendor and condition, we mounted our Sledges, and poſted three full hours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we diſcovered a Houſe; at length we perceived five or ſix, to them we went, and in them we found about a dozen per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, we asked if they had any. Furs they would part with, they told us yes, and having ſhewen us ſeveral we bought them, partly for ready mony and part for Strong Waters, of which thoſe people are very licquoriſh.</p>
               <p>We followed our journey by the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the River, obſerving Cabbins on both ſides of it, in ſome of them few, in others ſeveral People, of all of them we bought what we could get, ſometimes for Money, ſometimes for Strong-water, only their Sables they would not be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:42107:54"/>to ſell, apprehending they ſhould be found out by the Governour of <hi>Papinogo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> (whither we were going) who fails not to ſearch all Commodities that enter or paſs out of the Town, leaſt any of thoſe Sables ſhould be conveyed away by Stealth.</p>
               <p>We paſſed the Mountains which part <hi>Boranday</hi> from <hi>Siberia,</hi> they are very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant and troubleſom by reaſon of the wildneſs of the Country, uninhabitable both for the ſterility of the Soil, Snows which are perpetually upon them, and the vaſt quantity of Bears and White Wolfs which gave us no little fear during our Travels in thoſe parts, expecting to be ſet upon by them every moment, but we perceived they were no leſs fearful of us, flying us upon all encounters, ſome this, ſome that way, and all in great Conſternation, which we attributed much to the glittering of our Arms, by which we conceived they took us rather for Hunts-men then Merchants.</p>
               <p>After much labour to our Elks, and tediouſneſs to our ſelves, after twelve hours fatigue we deſcended the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and came into a Village belonging to <hi>Siberia,</hi> whoſe Inhabitants were all clad
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:42107:55"/>in Bears-skin, the hair on the outſide, but ſome linnen about them, and plated Boots, which made us believe them of better quality then their Neighbours which we had left. And indeed they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived us more civilly enquiring who we were, whence we came, and whither we were bound. We Eat and Drank with them of ſuch as we had, and they produced what their Town would afford, which was Bears-fleſh and Wolves Salted, with a ſort of Spice-bread, and <hi>aqua vitae:</hi> What Skins they had we bought with ready Money all but their Sables: and then having a deſire to reſt our ſelve; for ſome time, we entered into one of their houſes (made after the <hi>Laponian</hi> faſhion) and lay down upon Bears-skin about five or ſix hours, and then getting up again, we drank our Mornings draught together in <hi>aqua vitae,</hi> mounted our Sledges, and away for <hi>Papinogorod,</hi> where in about twenty hours time we arrived, having baited once or twice by the way to give our Cattel their neceſſary repaſt upon the Moſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:42107:55"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXII.</hi> The Reception of the <hi>Danes</hi> at <hi>Papinogo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> by the Governor, and the Authors among the reſt.</head>
               <p>THE Governor of <hi>Papinogorod</hi> hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our arrival, ſent for us to the Caſtle, to underſtand what we were, from whence we came, and what was our buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Upon his Summons we went to wait upon him, and after uſual Salutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (our Sub-Commiſs. ſpeaking the <hi>Muſcovian</hi> Language very well) we gave him ſatisfaction in every thing he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <p>When he underſtood we were <hi>Daniſh</hi> Merchants come thither only to buy Furs, he treated us very civilly, and in Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his great reſpect for us, and that he looked upon us as Friends, he ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Wife to come forth and ſalute us, which immediately ſhe did, bringing along with her (according to the cuſtome of the <hi>Muſcovits</hi>) a Bottle of Strong-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in one hand, a ſilver Cup in the other, and her Maid at her heels, with a piece of ſpic'd Bread upon a Trencher. The way
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:42107:56"/>of her ſaluting us was by bowing of her Head, and then undoing the wriſt-band of her Smock on the right Arm, ſhe let it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, and ſlide down upon the ground, which our Commiſs. (knowing the mode) very readily, and much like a Gentleman took up and kiſſed, and after him our Sub-Commiſs. and my ſelf, then holding up her right Arm She folded it up again with her left, and when 'twas done calling for her Cup and her Bottle, She began a Nog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen to each of us, and then preſented her Spice-Bread. She kept ſtill ſtanding at the end of the Table by her Husband, where after She had entertained us for ſome time, She returned to her Quarters, and we fell a drinking with the Governor, at length it grew late, and we were laid upon as good Beds as that Country will afford.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:42107:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIII.</hi> The <hi>Danes</hi> and the Authors Traffick in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinogorod,</hi> the ſcituation of the Town, with the habits and manners of the <hi>Sibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berians</hi> and <hi>Muſcovites.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SIx or ſeaven hours we repos'd in the Governors houſe before we aroſe, and he no ſooner heard us ſtirring, but up he got and came to us to our Chamber, with a bottle of <hi>Aqua-Vitae</hi> after him, which one of his ſervants brought in his hand. He himſelf took a Brimmer, and ſaw it go round, after which he asked us if we would buy what skins he had, which our Commiſs. promiſed if they were liked, and deſired to ſee them; being brought to us, we quickly ſtruck a bargain, and paid him his mony. When he had ſold all his own, he ſent for ſome of the Towns-men he knew were provided, and told them they might deal with us, and he would give them permiſſion; upon which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement we thought our ſelves obliged to the tother bottle.</p>
               <p>Whilſt our Commiſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Sub-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs. were imployed in driving their bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:42107:57"/>I took the opportunity to walk out into the Town. Its ſcituation is pleaſant enough, thoughin a little Mooriſh-Plain environed with very high Mountains; juſt by the Town there runs a fair River, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently well provided with Fiſh. The Houſes are but ill built, low, of Wood and Earth cram'd in betwixt the Rafters. 'Tis pav'd with nothing but pieces of Wood fitted as well as they can, and lying as cloſe as they can make them.</p>
               <p>The perſons of the beſt quality in that place, have their Breeches and Stockings, and a long Robe down to their anckles with their Sleeves very ſtraight, all of Cloth, but one of one colour, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of another. Upon their Legs they have thin Leather-Boots, ſome Blew, ſome Red, ſome Yellow, with Iron Plates at the Heel and the Toe, after the mode of the <hi>Polander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon their Heads they had Cloth-Caps fac'd ſome with black <hi>Fox,</hi> others with <hi>Squirrel,</hi> ſome with <hi>Ermins,</hi> and ſome <hi>Sables,</hi> according to their Fancy or Eſtate. The women were very handſome, fair and plump, their Hair a kind of yellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh brown, their faſhion extream well for <hi>Muſcovites.</hi> As their Husbands, ſo
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:42107:57"/>their Robes come down to their anckles, for the moſt part of Red, Violet colour, or Blew, made like our <hi>Juſte-au-Corps,</hi> lin'd with white <hi>Fox,</hi> or <hi>Sables,</hi> their Sleeves are large and hang down, being faſtned to their Robes, the length of their Smock-Sleeves is incredible, five Ells of a very fine Cotton Linnen is nothing for one of them; upon their Heads they wear a kind of an Oval-Cap, their Hair breid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and tyed up at the ends with Rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds which they let hang down upon their Shoulders. Their Shooes are made of a <hi>Ruſſian</hi> Wood, about their waſts they wear a Girdle of <hi>Pearl</hi> of no incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable bigneſs.</p>
               <p>The Natives of <hi>Siberia,</hi> are not much different from the <hi>Samojedes, Borandines,</hi> and other Northern people, either in their manners, habit, or manner of living.</p>
               <p>All the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> are <hi>Nicolaitans</hi> in matter of Religion, they are grave, ſtrong, ſwift, dexterous at their Bow, not at all contentious, their Laws being founded upon pure Equity. They are ſevere pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhers of Treachery, Prevarication, Thie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and Murder, and yet they are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ignorant, techy, drunken, clowniſh, and jealous, to that point, they make their
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:42107:58"/>Wives run and skud away into their Chambers upon the ſight of a ſtranger, where they are to continue Priſoners till they give the word of Command in ſhort their Slavery is ſuch, they dare not teſtify the leaſt friendſhip or civility for a ſtranger; nor do think their Husbands are kind, if they be not every day about their bones with agood Cudgel or Girdle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIV.</hi> The Authors departure from <hi>Papinogorod</hi> towards the Ships, his paſſage thorow <hi>Samoijeſia,</hi> with their manners, Cuſtoms, Veſtments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving bought what we could (which was a great quantity of <hi>Woolfs</hi>-skins white <hi>Fox,</hi> black <hi>Fox, Lynxes, Sables, Ermins,,</hi> and <hi>Squirrels</hi>) with the other we bought at <hi>Potzora,</hi> we filled one of our Sledges, and had a good many to ſpare. Having ſtore of Tobacco and about 5000. Ducates remaining, our Commiſs. and Sub-Commiſs. were willing to diſpoſe of them for more Furs, and therefore reſolv'd to return to our Ships thorow <hi>Samoijeſia.</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:42107:58"/>To that end they bought of our Hoſt the Governor of <hi>Papinogorod,</hi> as much ſtrong water and other proviſions as would laſt us for twelve days. Our bargain being ſtruck, both for proviſions and <hi>Elks,</hi> and the mony paid, we were forced to have another debauch with him of ten hours long, after which we ſlept eight more: and then, our Sledges being ready, our goods and proviſions packed up, and put into one of them, we got in our ſelves, and taking leave of the Governour we departed.</p>
               <p>About eighteen hours we were upon the march, buying skins as we paſſed as far as the <hi>Riphean</hi> Mountains, which in our entrance into <hi>Samoijeſia,</hi> we croſſed in ſix hours more. <hi>Samoijefia</hi> is a deſert Country, full of <hi>Juniper, Pine-Trees,</hi> and <hi>Firr;</hi> it abounds in <hi>Moſs,</hi> in <hi>Snow, Woolfs, Bears, Foxes,</hi> all white, which we met every moment, and they gave us no little apprehenſion.</p>
               <p>At the bottom of the Mountain call'd <hi>Stolpohen</hi> (from whence the River <hi>Borza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gane</hi> ſprings) we ſaw eight or nine Houſes and made towards them, both to reſt our ſelves, and refreſh our <hi>Elks,</hi> with the Inhabitants of which we fell immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:42107:59"/>a trucking our ſtrong-water for their <hi>Woolf, Fox,</hi> (white and black) <hi>Beaver,</hi> and <hi>Otter</hi>-skins, beſide which they had two <hi>Limmers</hi> of <hi>Sables</hi> which they would not be drawn to part with by all the peſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and proteſtations our <hi>Boran dine</hi> Guide could make, that they need not fear; that we were Merchants paſſing to our Ships, and would not go by any place where there was danger of being ſearched. But nothing would do, they would not hearken till we made them drunk, and then they parted with them freely, the vapours of the ſtrong-water having more effect upon them than all our <hi>Borandins</hi> Rhetorick. For that night we made a ſhift with one of their Cabanes, and lay higglede-pigglede with the Wife, Husband Barns, Servants, Cattel and all. Five or ſix hours after, I awaked at the noiſe the Maſter made to get up his Family, and as ſoon as they were up, they went all out of Doors.</p>
               <p>I had a Curioſity to ſee what they did, and watching them a while, I ſaw them clap themſelves down upon their knees, on the other ſide of the Houſe, holding up their hands, and make ſeveral ſignes of adoration to the <hi>Sun,</hi> which they believe to be God.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:42107:59"/>
               <p>The <hi>Samoides</hi> are thicker and ſhorter, then either the <hi>Laponians</hi> or <hi>Borandines.</hi> Their Head is larger, their Face broader, their Noſe bigger and flatter, they have little or no hair, and are of a duskiſh and earthy Complexion. Their Veſtments for the men, are a Round Bonnet frizled as it was made of Lambskins, their Bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and long Robe of white <hi>Bears</hi>-skin which reaches below their knees, they are tyed under the Belly with a Girdle four fingers broad, their Stockings and Shooes of the ſame Leather, with the Hair out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and under their Shooes a kind of a Pattin made of the Bark of a Tree in the ſaſhion of a <hi>Gondelo,</hi> which went all along under their feet, and ſerv'd to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them with ſtrange ſwiftneſs over the <hi>Snow,</hi> which on thoſe Mountains lies ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thick; In ſtead of a Cloak, they have a black skin, with the four feet hanging to it, by-which they carry it more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently upon the left Shoulder than the right; and upon their Cloak they carry their Quiver.</p>
               <p>The women in this Country are more ill-favour'd than the men. They are very laborious, take great pains to learn their Children to Hunt, upon which they live
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:42107:60"/>altogether, and upon nothing elſe. Their Habit is like the Mens, only their Robe ſomething longer, and no Cloak upon their Shoulders; they have the ſame co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver for their heads, they have only one tuft of hair twiſted and tyed at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom with a Ribbond (made of the Rind of a Tree) which hangs down upon their backs: they go a hunting Arm'd with their Bow and Arrowes like the Men, and are every way as dexterous.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIV.</hi> The Author departs from <hi>Boranday</hi> to go to go to <hi>Nova Zembla,</hi> where he ſaw a Troop of them worſhiping the Sun, and two others paying their devotions to a wooden Idol they call <hi>Tetizot,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving paſſed thorow <hi>Samojeſia,</hi> and being returned into the Country of <hi>Boranday</hi> towards our Ships that expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with impatience, we got on Board as ſoon as we could, and two hours after we ſet Sail for <hi>Nova Zembla.</hi> In twenty hours time we arrived at a place where we ſaw about thirty perſons with their Quivers at their Backs, upon their Kneeson
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:42107:60"/>the ſhoar worſhiping the Sun. Our Maſters and Commiſſioners call'd a Counſel to conſider which way we were to accoſt theſe people whom we looked upon as more Savage and unciviliz'd than any we had met. The reſult was we ſhould ſet out three of our Shallops with ten men a peice in them, well Arm'd in caſe of oppoſition, among which I was commanded to make one; we coaſted along the Shore till we came within half a quarter of a League of them, when the Natives (till then upon their Knees) leaped up upon their Feet, made a great Cry, and having ſhot all their Arrowes againſt us, fled away like hunted Deer, but they ſhot too far off to do us any harm</p>
               <p>Being got on Shore as we could, we made with all ſpeed towards the place whether we ſuppoſed they were ran, with intentions if poſſible to have ſeiz'd upon ſome of them, but we were diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of our deſigne, they having got out of our ſight, and we not able to gueſs which way they were gone, however we marched towards the Mountains, found them all covered with Snow, and having paſſed them, advanced into the Plains; upon the Stump of Trees newly cut down
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:42107:61"/>we ſaw ſeveral Images of Men Carv'd ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very coarſly, and before one of them near a League from us we could perceive two of thoſe Savages upon their Knees, (their Bows and Arrowes laid by them) paying their devotions. When they diſcovered us, they roſe up in a fright whip'd up their Arms and away in the ſame haſt and apprehenſion as they had done whom we had ſurpriſed on the Shore in their adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sun.</p>
               <p>We made what ſpeed we could after them, to have taken them if poſſible, but they were too nimble and got into a wood of Firs before we could come near them. returning to our Ships, we ſaw at a great diſtance two more at their Idolatry, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiping another Statue of the ſame called by the Natives <hi>Tetiz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t,</hi> into which the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel enters and delivers our his Oracles, as our Maſter of the Ship told us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:42107:61"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXV.</hi> Of the Diſeaſe called the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> with which the Author and moſt part of the <hi>Danes</hi> in that Voiage were ſurpriſed.</head>
               <p>I Had not been on board above ſeaven or eight hours before I was ſurprized with a violent pain in my head, and a diſpoſition to Vomit, which continued three or four hours, after which I was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with a ſoarneſs in my throat which hindred my ſwallowing, I had a great ſwelling in my Amants, accompanied with an Ebullition of my blood, and a ſtrong itching all over my Body, my Gums were inflamed, and bled very much, my Teeth ſo looſe I expected they would fall out every moment, nor could I endure to eat any thing that was hard. My Body became very weak, and Feavoriſh, my breath ſhort, with a very ill Savour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a great drought, for the cure of which I frequently drank <hi>Oxierat.</hi> Fifteen hours after finding my diſtemper continue and conſidering it proceeded in part from a great cold I had upon me, &amp; my eating of ſalt meats, which had irritated my petui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:42107:62"/>glandule, &amp; envenum'd it in ſuch ſort that the Rheume infected my other hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, I reſolved inſtead of <hi>Oxierat,</hi> to drink <hi>Aqua-Vitae</hi> mingled with fair water, I made alſo a Syrrop of Liquoriſh, of which I took the quantity of a ſpoonful every hour, gargling often ſometimes with <hi>Aqua-Vitae,</hi> ſometimes with <hi>Vinegar</hi> to refreſhmy Gums, and rubbed my teeth with hony of Roſes. Moſt of our Ships Crew being troubled with the ſame di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, uſed the ſame remedy, and it was ſo effectual to us all not one of us miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried.</p>
               <p>Thoſe of the other Ships were not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt, they had the ſame diſeaſe as well as we, in ſo much the Chyrurgions of their ſeveral Ships were put to it to cure them; the method they took was by Phlebotomy and purging, but that made them rather worſe than better, in ſo much that in one of their Veſſels there dyed two Seamen, in the other three, and a Sub-Commiſs. and all in ſix days time; doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs more of them had followed had not, they followed my Counſel, which was to leave their bleeding and purging (which in that diſtemper are mortal) and betake to my remedy. I remember in the year 1670.
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:42107:62"/>in the Winter the violence of the cold put many people in <hi>Paris</hi> into the ſame diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, the Phyſitians took it for a kind of a Plague, and thinking by bleeding and Purgation to recover their Patients, ſent many of them to the Grave.</p>
               <p>When I was in <hi>Algier,</hi> ſeveral people were troubled with the Scurvy, thoſe that were infected had their Amants ſwell'd as if they had had a piece of Fleſh in their Mouths, and all the Symptoms I have mentioned before, engendred as before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid by a ſharp defluction that vitiated the reſt of the humors but eſpecially the blood, in the ſame manner almoſt as it is in the French Pox, there being a ſort of it ſo like; among the <hi>Indians</hi> they have the ſame name, and are called <hi>Pieans.</hi> For which reaſon I took the ſame way of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Scurvy as they do the Pox, as is to be ſeen in my <hi>Hiſtory of the State of the Kingdom of</hi> Algier, <hi>Couque, Titican,</hi> &amp;c. as alſo in my Treatiſe <hi>De lue Venerea.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:42107:63"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVI.</hi> Our Fiſhing for the Sea Horſe, with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation how two of our Mariners were drowned by the motion of one of their Tails.</head>
               <p>HAving continued fifteen or ſixteen days at Anchor upon the Coaſts of <hi>Zembla</hi> for the convenience of our ſick, all of them being recovered except ſome few, the weather coming fair, our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters reſolved to weigh and ſtand off to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Voygat</hi> in order to our Fiſhing for the <hi>Sea-Horſe:</hi> accordingly we put about three Leagues to Sea, cruiſing up and down the Coaſts at that diſtance, and ſending out our Shallops with their hooks and Hatchets, and eight men in each of them to ſee what they could catch.</p>
               <p>Three days we were before we ſaw any thing, at length we ſaw two great Fiſhes (one of them with a Horn of a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable length) which our Fiſhermen put themſelves into a poſture to take, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing got within a ſtones caſt of them, they threw out their Hooks, ſome on one ſide, ſome on the other with long lines faſtned
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:42107:63"/>to them for the purpoſe and then came back again with all ſpeed to our Ships.</p>
               <p>Being got on Board our Ships, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Fiſh ſwimming above water (which is a ſigne it was ſpent) by little and little they drag'd it towards the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, which it ſuffered without reluctance, the loſs of blood having rendred it weak, and then falling to with our Axes, we cut of its head which we kept, but threw the body into the Sea, as being unfit ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for Victual or Oyl. Our fiſhing for the <hi>Sea-Horſe</hi> is only for its teeth, which is uſefull as Ivory for all kind of curioſity, and ſells much dearer in reſpect of its whiteneſs (which is far better of the two) and laſts longer before it turns red.</p>
               <p>The Horn of this <hi>Sea-horſe,</hi> was full ten foot long, very heavy, wreathed like a Snail and as big as the biggeſt part of a mans Arm, tapering from the head to the point which was as ſharp as a nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle.</p>
               <p>One of our Shallops coming too near the other Fiſh before they threw out their Irons, finding her ſelf ſtruck ſhe gave ſuch a frisk with her Tail, that hitting the Boat, it turned it over, and before their Camrades could poſſibly relieve them, two
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:42107:64"/>of them were drowned, which troubled us much; how ever the Fiſh was taken and loſt her head, as that we took had done before. I went to ſee it three or four hours after, found it had no Horn, but the want of that was well recompenced in her Teeth, which were much the fairer of the two.</p>
               <p>Four days and nights we were cruiſing up and down after we had taken theſe two before we met with any more; and juſt as we were removing to ſome other place, we diſcovered four of the ſame ſort, in appearance much bigger than thoſe we had taken. Upon which we ſlackned our Sail, let down our Shallops, with our Iron-mongers, and ſuch other people as were neceſſary for that imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in a ſhort time they had catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed three of the four: the other eſcaping, that our Fiſhermen brought on board our Ship had no Horn, nor indeed the other two. Ten or twelve hours after we ſaw five more, we put down our people with their Irons, their Hooks and their Hatchets, and what elſe was neceſſary for the purpoſe to try what they could do in our Shallops, eſpecially with one of them which we had obſerved to have a horn:
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:42107:64"/>but in ſpight of all the diligence could be uſed we could take but two; three of them got off, and that with the Horn was one of them. Some three hours after we perceived three more, of which our Officers catched one, whoſe Head was ſo big each of its great teeth weighed near thirty pounds.</p>
               <p>Two days after we diſcerned ſeaven or eight of them, and one with a Horn, we ſet out all our Shallops immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and were ſo fortunate in the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, we took five of them, and that with the Horn was one of the number: it was brought to our Ship, but the Horn was neither ſo heavy, ſo big, nor ſo long as the other.</p>
               <p>Having kept our ſtation five days after, and diſcovered nothing, a <hi>N. N. W.</hi> Wind riſing on a ſuddain, we took the opportunity and made all the Sail we could to <hi>Voygat,</hi> hoping to paſs it by the benifit of that if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, but being got about five and twenty Leagues into that Sea, we durſt venture no farther by reaſon of the Mountains of Ice which ſtopped up the paſſage into the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Sea, into which if by this paſſage an entrance could be found
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:42107:65"/>it would ſhorten the Voyage to the Eaſt <hi>Indies</hi> three parts in four, which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by the Name, <hi>Voygat</hi> in their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage ſignifying <hi>ſhorter cut.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVII.</hi> The boldneſs of the Bears upon the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of <hi>Voygat.</hi> The taking of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Birds which the <hi>Danes</hi> call <hi>Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goins.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE had not been above five or ſix hours at Anchor, before one of our Sea men being on Shore about his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary occaſions, a great Bear came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, and patting him with his foot ſtrook him clear over; without doubt he had been devoured, had not we ſpyed it by accident, and ſhooting at it from on Board, killed it dead upon the place, and reſcued the poor Mariner from the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt fright he was ever in in his Life. Not long after there came to one of our ſhips two Bears which attempted to have got in we cut off the paws of one of them with our Hatchets as it was clambring up the ſides of it, and the other we ſhot. Being
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:42107:65"/>all ſtaring, and imployed about the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of them two; a Sea man from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind us cryed out as if he had been mad, and not without reaſon, for three more having come ſwimming towards our Ship one of them had got up, and boarded us, but ſnatching up our Oars, Poles, and what other engines we had ready, we belaboured him ſo about the head, we quickly laid him aſleep, and killed the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with our Guns. we thought then we were ſafe, and ſhould be troubled with them no more, but we reckoned without our Hoſt: for four or five hours after we were alarm'd by eight or ten more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing upon the Ice, and (when that failed) throwing themſelves into the Sea, and ſwiming towards our Ships, which made us ſtand to our Arms, and when we ſaw them within diſtance, we fir'd ſo ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesfully upon them, ſcarce one of them eſcaped.</p>
               <p>Theſe Creatures coming down from the Mountains in ſuch great numbers (as if they looked upon our being there as an Invaſion, and were got together on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to repell us) gave us ſome apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and was partly the cauſe we weighed Anchor, and returned from whence we came.</p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:42107:66"/>
               <p>Having Sailed above twelve hours to diſingage our ſelves from that ſtreight with the favour of an Eaſterly wind, and yet with great difficulty by reaſon of the ice, we came to a Anchor under a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Iſland, all delicatly green by the verdure of the <hi>Moſs,</hi> the <hi>Fir</hi>-Trees, and the <hi>Juniper.</hi> Some of our Sea-men going a Shore, ſaw a ſort of foul which could ſcarce fly for their fat, giving us an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it at their return, I was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded out (with forty more taken out of all our Ships) to go on ſhore and try what we could catch of them, and indeed in no long time partly with our Guns, and partly with our Cudgels, we brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout threeſcore of them along with us when we returned.</p>
               <p>Theſe Birds (which our Maſters told us were called <hi>Pingoins</hi>) are no higher than Swans, but much thicker; they are as white as they, their neck as long as Gooſes, their head bigger, with a red ſparkling Eye a bout the breadth of a ſhilling, the beak is yellowiſh and ſharp, the feet broad and firm like a Gooſes. They have a kind of a purſe about a foot long which begins under their beaks, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues all along their necks to the very
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:42107:66"/>breaſt where it inlarges to ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree it will hold a full Pottle. In this it is (when their bellies are full) they lay up their Cud, to have it ready again when their Stomacks require.</p>
               <p>Before we could eat them we were forced to skin them, it being extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hard, and the Feathers not to be pulled out of it but with very great difficulty. The Fleſh is good, has the ſame taſt with a wild-Duck, is very fat, and made us very good Chear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVIII.</hi> Of <hi>a Zemblian</hi> which had like to have been taken by us; of another and his Wife taken in their <hi>Canoe,</hi> with their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of building.</head>
               <p>HAving continued at Anchor two days and nights near this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland where we took our <hi>Pingoins,</hi> the wind coming favourably about to the <hi>E. S. E.</hi> we weighed, and ſtood to the <hi>N. N. W.</hi> and a while after (having cleered our ſelves of the ſtrait) the wind changing we were obliged to change,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:42107:67"/>with it, and ſteer our courſe upon the Coaſts <hi>E. N. E.</hi> towards the height of the Cape, where in thirty hours time we arrived near the place in which we ſaw the <hi>Zemblans</hi> adoring the <hi>Sun.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Majeſty of <hi>Denmark,</hi> having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it in Charge to our Maſters and Commiſs. if they found any people in <hi>Zembla,</hi> they ſhould endeavour to take ſome of them, that by them he might gain information what was done in that Country, we came to Anchor in that place, and ſent out our Shallops to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, to this purpoſe thirty men were commanded on ſhore in four Shallops, and in one of them my ſelf.</p>
               <p>We had ſcarce left our Ships, but we deſcryed about half a League from the Shore a <hi>Zemblane</hi> in a <hi>Canoe,</hi> who percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us make toward him rowed with might and main to clear himſelf of us, and having gained the Shore, he whip'd his <hi>Canoe</hi> upon his Shoulder, clapped his Bow and Arrowes in it, and taking his Dart in the other hand, away he ran (like the Philoſopher) with his whole eſtate at his Back. We got to ſhore as ſoon as we could, and followed him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Spur up a little Hill we obſerved
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:42107:67"/>him to climb, but being nimbler than we, we could not poſſibly reach him; we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to our Shallops as wiſe as we went, much troubled he had given us the Slip; as we were rowing towards our Ships, we deſcry'd two <hi>Zemblans</hi> a good way at Sea, rowing like mad towards the Rocks and the Promontories to hide themſelves from us, as ſoon as they perceived us. We no ſooner diſcovered them, but we made after them with all ſpeed, and though they uſed all the ſtrength and Art they were able to have got to a Rock, we reached them before they came there, and having taken them, they made the moſt horrid and diſmal yell, I ever heard in my life. We brought them to our Veſſel, and drew them up with Ropes in their <hi>Canoe,</hi> which was made in the faſhion of a <hi>Gondelo,</hi> fifteen or ſixteen foot long, and two foot and a half broad made of fiſh-Ribs very artificially, covered without with Fiſh-skins ſowed together, which made the whole <hi>Canoe</hi> from one end to the other not unlike a purſe, in which the two <hi>Zemblans</hi> were incloſed to the waſt, in ſuch ſort that not a drop of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter could get into it, and they might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves in the greateſt Storm
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:42107:68"/>without any danger in the world. We perceived they were Man and Woman, made all the Careſſes, and ſignes of ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to them we could think of to tempt them to ſhew us their habitations, but unable to prevail any thing upon them, we took proviſions for ten or twelve days, and about thirty of us went a ſhore, well Arm'd, and divided into two parties, we marched about an hundred paces from one another, till at length getting under the Rocks, we hid our ſelves in the holes, clapping Sentinels upon the Trees to diſcover if any Savages were to be ſeen that we might take ſome of them, and be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to their Houſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIX.</hi> The taking of another <hi>Zemblane</hi> and his Wife, their Habits, Arms, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of living.</head>
               <p>IT was not much leſs than eight and fourty hours we were thus upon the watch, when one of our Sentinels gave notice he diſcovered two of the <hi>Zemblans</hi> coming down a little Hill towards the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:42107:68"/>Sea. We diſpoſed our ſelves immediately with what advantage we could, ſix of us remain'd in the Cave where we were, five and my ſelf removed farther off into another, and in a quarter of an hours time they paſſed betwixt our <hi>Ambuſcades</hi> without perceiving any thing of us; one of our party gave the Signal by firing of a Gun, as well to give the other the alarm, as to ſtop the <hi>Zemblans</hi> and make them look about them, it ſucceeded as we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, and Whilſt they were in a maze we leapt both parties from our Ambuſhment, encompaſſed them ſo they could not eſcape and took them.</p>
               <p>Their Veſtments were of the skins of <hi>Pingoins</hi> with the Feathers upon them. They conſiſted of very ſtrait Breeches which reached no lower than the knees, a Waſtcoat of the ſame, the ſleeves reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no farther than the Elbows, the reſt of their Arm being naked; Their Waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coats were cut with a Peak, before and behind like a Tail, their Caps upon their Heads were like Sugar-Loav's, their Boots were of the skin of a Sea-Calf, of a red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh brown colour, the hair outward.</p>
               <p>Though they were both habited alike, we could diſcern one was a Man and the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:42107:69"/>other a Woman. The Man was about twenty years old, a broad Face like thoſe we had taken before, of a ſwarthy brown, his noſe big and flat, his eyes little and drawn towards his Temples without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Beard or Hair, his Quiver was full of Arrowes at his Back with a hatchet of Fiſh-Bones, which he carried upon his Shoulder with one hand, and his dart in the other.</p>
               <p>The woman was about twenty years old, her hair in two breids hanging down upon her Shoulders, ſhe had blew ſtreaks all along her Chin, and three or four up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her forehead, on her ears and under her Noſe holes had been made, and blew ſtones hanged in them in little Rings made of the ſmal bones of Fiſh. Thoſe in her Ears were as big as Filbeards thoſe in her noſe were like Peaſe, and to defend her jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els ſhe carried a Dart in her hand.</p>
               <p>We uſed all the Artifice we could to have prevailed with them to ſhow us their quarters, but nothing would do, and we were forced to carry them on Board, where we put them to the other two we had taken in the <hi>Canoe:</hi> we could perceive they knew one another preſently, though their habit was different, the firſt we
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:42107:69"/>took not being clad in Feathers, but in the skins of Sea-Calfs, with the hair out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, their Waſtcoats being made of two skins ſowed together, with their Tails hanging down one before, and another behind as low as their Thighs, and their Drawers were very ſtrait. The eldeſt was about fifty years old, with a round Cheſt-nut coloured Beard, but no hair on his head. His Lady was about thirty, her Ears and noſe pierced (like other perſons of her quality) and laden with blew ſtones her Hair was platted in two Locks hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon her Shoulders, with blew ſtreaks upon her Chin and her Forehead, in ſhort there was never a Barrel better Herring, one as rich and ill favoured as the other, both little trubs like the <hi>Samojedes, Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers, Borandians,</hi> and <hi>Siberians,</hi> their voice was ſhrill and ſqueaking their breath ſtunk abominably, which we imputed to their Diet, eating their meat without Salt, or elſe dabbling their Fiſh in the Oyl of another ſort of Fiſh. They drank no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but water, we could never get them to touch a piece of bread, to eat a bit of our ſalt meat, or ſalt Fiſh, nor ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low one drop of Beer. We tempted them a little with our ſtrong water,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:42107:70"/>but the ſmell of Toboccco they abhor'd.</p>
               <p>All their work was wrought with thread made of Fiſh-skin, their needles with which they ſowed, of the ſmall bones of Fiſh, the end of their Darts and generally all their tools of their bigger bones,</p>
               <p>The wood of their Darts and their Bowes were very heavy, of a kind of a red Brown, but their Arrowes were much lighter, of a Whiter Wood, and they ſhot them with great dexterity. To make the women compleat they both of them wadled like Ducks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XL.</hi> Our departure from <hi>Zembla</hi> in Order to our return. Our arrival in <hi>Greenland,</hi> the <hi>Whale</hi>-Fiſhing, and the way they make Oyl of them.</head>
               <p>THe year being far ſpent, and the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of <hi>Auguſt</hi> already come, the days began to ſhorten, and we had half an hour night, beſides the cold increaſing upon us, it was judged beſt (having a
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:42107:70"/>fair <hi>N. N. E.</hi> Wind) to weigh Anchor and ſtand to the <hi>S. W.</hi> we had not ſail'd many hours before the wind came about <hi>S. S. E.</hi> which forced us to our former Northern courſe, to gain the Coaſts if we could, which we did, and by the favour of that wind ſailed by them as far as <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where being catched with a <hi>W. S. W.</hi> wind, we were obliged to caſt Anchor again near a great number of French and Dutch Veſſels which lay near the ſhore a fiſhing for <hi>Whale,</hi> which Fiſhing is much after the rate of the Sea-Horſe. Having ſtruck it with their Irons, they draw it gently towards the Shore, and when it is dead, cut it all into Mamocks, for the fat, which they melt in great Kettles to draw out the Oyl, not far from certain Cabanes which the Fiſhermen build for that purpoſe upon the Coaſt.</p>
               <p>This happened very luckily for our <hi>Zemblians,</hi> their Stomachs were almoſt loſt for want of oyl, for two days together they had had none to dip their Fiſh in, becauſe it grew ſcarce in the Ship, and we were forc'd to abate their allowance of oyl with the Fiſh we gave them to eat.</p>
               <p>I ſaw them order one of their Whales, and ſtood by till they had done. They
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:42107:71"/>drew out of her as much Whale-bone as weighed three hundred and fifty pound weight, which they reſerved for the Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers for Busks and bodies for the Ladies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLI.</hi> The Authors departure from <hi>Greenland,</hi> three Suns appear to him at Sea; by a violent Tempeſt the Ships are driven upon the Coaſt of <hi>Iſland.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving continued two days upon the Coaſt of <hi>Greenland,</hi> a <hi>N. E.</hi> wind ariſing, we weighed Anchor in perſuit of our journy, keeping half Sea over, and ſteering <hi>W. S. W.</hi> All the firſt day the wind was favourable, and held ſo till a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout five next morning, at which time turning quite contrary to <hi>E. S. E.</hi> we deſcern'd three Suns in the Firmament one above another, ſo clear and conſpicuous, we could not tell which was the right, and more towards the South we found the sky begin to thicken, and lower, upon which our Maſter told the Pilot we were in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a Storm; in that apprehenſion we took down moſt of our Sails, and gave
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:42107:71"/>our Companions a Gun as a ſignal they ſhould do the ſame, after which we fell to prayers, expecting ſubmiſſively the pleaſure of God.</p>
               <p>Not many hours paſſed before we were overtaken by a ſtrong <hi>S. S: E.</hi> Wind, a violent Rain, and ſuch dreadful claps of Thunder, we thought the World had been at an end. The Sea on the other ſwell'd and raged exceedingly, ſo as we were able to keep up none but our Mizain Sail, our Sail yard was very low, and two of our Sea men were forced to keep our long Boats on Board by the Ropes they had faſtned to them on purpoſe; and indeed we had much ado to manage our Ship.</p>
               <p>Having been toſſed in this manner all that day and night, without any abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Wind, our Maſter command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up one of the Seamen to the Scuttle, to ſee if he could diſcover any land, that we might know where we were. Our Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man after he had looked about him ſome time cryed out to us that he diſcovered <hi>W. N. W.</hi> of us a great fire, which our Maſter concluded muſt needs be <hi>Hecla,</hi> a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in <hi>Iſland,</hi> and though we had no buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> yet the Wind continuing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> barter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:42107:72"/>our Ships, and obſtructing our Sail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we reſolved to make thither, and ſee what ſhelter we could find; according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſteering our courſe that way, we arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon the Coaſts in not many hours, and all that Night (lying under that Mountain) we heard moſt diſmal and ſtrange noiſes like the ſhooting of great Guns, we ſaw great Fires and flames riſing out of it in abundance.</p>
               <p>The multitude of Rocks we found up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ſhore, and the fierceneſs of the Sea, made us afraid to come too near; but by the skill and diligence of our Pilot we came to an Anchor under Cape <hi>Hori</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any inconvenience. One of the ſhips of our Company whoſe Pilot was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſo dexterous or experienced as ours, within a ſmall diſtance of us ran his Stem againſt a Rock, brake a piece of it off, and the whole Veſſel was in no lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle danger of daſhing to pieces, the third came off well, and had no more harm than we.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:42107:72"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLII.</hi> The Authors going on ſhoar, his arrival at <hi>Kirkebar;</hi> his Voyage to <hi>Hecla,</hi> the danger he ran there; the marvellous ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of two Fountains which ſpring out of that Hill, and other particulars.</head>
               <p>HAving put on Shore with our Maſter, our Commiſs. and others to the number of fifteen (part out of our Veſſel, and part out of the reſt) we advanced to <hi>Hori,</hi> (which is a Town about a League and an half from the Sea) and from thence to <hi>Kirkebar</hi> (a little Town or a great Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage which you will, in that Iſland) we found in <hi>Kirkebar</hi> a Commiſs. and ſeven or eight Daniſh Merchants, who were ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to ſee us there. They told us they were very glad to ſee us, and that the day before they had had ſuch an Earth-quake they thought the whole Iſland would have ſunk into the Sea. They treated us with good wine, good bread, and good freſh meat. They have great plenty of Cattel in that Iſland, which (by reaſon of the ſweetneſs of the Paſture ground with which it abounds) the Inhabitants are
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:42107:73"/>forced to feed by meaſure, leaſt they ſhould otherwiſe burſt themſelves, which would certainly happen if they ſuffered them to eat what they would, as in other Countries they do.</p>
               <p>Our Maſter, our Commiſs. and ſome others deſiring to ſee farther, and intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it to the Commiſs. of <hi>Kirkebar,</hi> he cauſed Horſes to be got ready for them. I told them I had a mind to be of the party and they received me into their number; eight of us took Horſe (leaving the reſt who were not ſo curious) and departed in the Company of two of the Commiſs. of <hi>Kirkebars</hi> Servants, and two Iſlanders (ſent along as Guides) with a Horſe-load of Proviſions. Two days together we travelled over Mountains, craggy, and unfrequented ways towards <hi>Hecla.</hi> Being arrived within a League and half of it, we found the ground all covered with aſhes and Pumice Stones, over which we were forced to march to the bottom of the Mountain.</p>
               <p>The sky being ſerene, and no flames to bee ſeen from the Mountain, we took a reſolution to go up to the top of it, but our Guides (to divert us) gave us to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that if we paſſed any farther, we
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:42107:73"/>ſhould run a great hazard of ſinking into holes the Fire had made, from whence there would be no poſſibility to recover us upon which the whole company being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, changed their minds and were returning as they came, but I told them if they would have patience, and ſtay till I came back, I would venture alone, and give them an account; they promiſed they would, and one of the Merchants we found at <hi>Kirkebar</hi> (who in curioſity had come with us) undertook to bear me Company.</p>
               <p>We preſently alighted, giving our Horſes to our Guides (who ſtaid with the Gentlemen) and marched over the aſhes and Pumices (mid leg deep) towards the top, where we ſaw a great quantity of Birds flying up and down as black as pitch, and they were Crowes and Vultures which build there.</p>
               <p>Being got about half a League up the Hill, we found it begin to tremble under our feet, and heard a ſtrange craſhing and rumbling within, which argued a hollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and gave us no little fear of ſinking into it; at the ſame time round about us, on this ſide, and on that we perceived great chincks, out of which flames and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:42107:74"/>ſparkles came forth, and noiſome, and ſtinking of burned Brimſtone, which frighted us ſo, we were glad to get back again as faſt as we could for fear of being ſwallowed. Being got about thirty pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces back, a cloud of Aſhes brake ſodain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the Mountain (ſo big and thick it obſcured the Sun) and fell upon us in ſuch manner, we could not ſee one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that which frighted us the moſt vvas to ſee every moment nevv guſts of Fire and Aſhes break out freſh and fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us like hail, vvith a continued noiſe and rumbling under us, vvhich made us try out moſt rufully as if all the infernal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uries had deſigned to overvvhelm us, expecting every moment vvhen the Earth ſhould open and ſvvallovv us, to prevent vvhich vve made uſe of our heels, and ran dovvn again as faſt as our legs could carry us, to avoid the danger into vvhich our cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity had brought us.</p>
               <p>Our fear added ſuch vvings to our feet, and gave us ſuch agility of body, that in a quarter of an hour vve had not only got the Mountain, but recovered our friends vvho attended us, and could not forbear laughing to ſee the pickle vve vvere in, our fear &amp; the aſhes together having rendred us
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:42107:74"/>as black as if we had been plung'd in a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of inck. But their laughter was quickly over, when they ſaw us fall down at their feet as if we had been dead, our ſpirits and our ſpeech failing us; to recover us they rubbed our Temples, pulled us by the Noſes, and gave us Vinegar to ſmell to.</p>
               <p>After ſometime being come to our ſelves we took each of us a Cup of Sack, which recovered our ſences, and then we depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, coaſting along about a hundred paces from the Mountain, towards two Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, one of them ſo hot it perpetually boyled, the other ſo cold it turned every thing put into it into ſtone.</p>
               <p>We ſaw a Pumice ſtone about the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a Hogſhead, which had been thrown from that Mountain a little before, whilſt we were admiring how it ſhould be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, one of our Guides told us he had ſeen much greater, and among the reſt one which ten men were not able to move he told us moreover beſides the Fire, Flames, Cinders, and Aſhes we had ſeen, it throwes out ſometimes ſcalding hot wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſometimes flames, ſometimes Fire, and ſometimes nothing but ſtones,</p>
               <p>After the expence of three full howers,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:42107:75"/>we arrived at the Fountains (which are not diſtant from one another above thirty paces) and coming firſt to the Cold I put in a ſwitch I had in my hand, and having pulled it out again, was much ſurprized to ſee the end which had touched the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome metamorphoſed into Iron, and full as heavy. From thence we went to the hot ſpring, in which (at about ten paces diſtance) we ſaw a multitude of Foul as big as Dydoppers (moſt of them red) play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and skipping together upon the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, with which we were much pleaſed, and ſtopped for ſome time for fear of interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, but when at length we appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, they all diſappeared, and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring again, they began to ſhow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as before; which it ſeems is their way when no body diſturbs them, but as ſoon as any thing comes near them, down they go all of them to the bottom of the Fountain, which by the report of our Guides is little leſs than ſixty fathom deep.</p>
               <p>From theſe Fountains we pointed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Sea, and being come within half a League of it, we could hear a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain noiſe as it were bemoaning and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting ſome diſaſter, which our Guides
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:42107:75"/>would fain have perſwaded me (as they had done other people) were the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of the damned whom the Divel tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, refreſhing them ſometimes Civil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the Ice in that place, after they had dry roaſted in the flames of <hi>Hecla.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We all concurred in a curioſity to ſee that Ice (there being none beſides there about all the Iſland) we no ſooner came near it, but I perceived the imaginary yells and Lamentations of the damned, proceded from that Ice and nothing elſe by the agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the wind and the water, and a perpetual concuſſion one piece againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or all of them againſt the Rocks.</p>
               <p>Theſe Ices (if we may take the word of our Guides) do conſtantly come about the latter end of <hi>June,</hi> and diſappear the fifteenth of <hi>September,</hi> which was within two days after we were there.</p>
               <p>Foom thence we departed in our return to <hi>Kirkebar,</hi> where we arrived three days after, and from thence to our Ships, in which we found the Governor of the Iſland accompanied with the Biſhop of <hi>Scalhoult</hi> who were come to ſee them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the news of our arrival, and that we had been at <hi>Zembla.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="chapter">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:42107:76"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIII.</hi> The habitation, manner of living and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition of the Iſlanders, with other particularities.</head>
               <p>FOr the moſt part the Iſlanders have their habitations in holes cut in the Rocks, but ſome of them have their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banes, as they have in <hi>Laponia,</hi> ſome made of the bones of Fiſhes, ſome of wood, covered over with Turffs of earth, their Cattel and themſelves being Chamber-Fellowes, and under one Roof: The men are very homely, the women little better, ſwarthy moſt of them as the <hi>Norwegians</hi> are, their Coats are generally Canvas, but ſome of them, are in Sea-Calfs-skin with the hair outward.</p>
               <p>Their manner of living (like the reſt of the Northern Countries) is very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural; their lodging is upon dryed hearbs with skins thrown over them, and one bed of that kind ſerves the whole Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>Their whole imployment is Fiſhing. They are very ſlovenly, rude, bruitiſh, and moſt of them Sorcerers, worſhiping
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:42107:76"/>the Divel (which they call <hi>Kobalde</hi>) who appears to them often in humane ſhape: they have another Idol of wood, cut moſt hideouſly with a Knife, which they ſhow but ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ldome for ſcar it ſhould be ſtolen or demoliſhed by certain <hi>Lutheran</hi> Prieſts which are there to inſtruct them in the doctrine of Chriſtianity, and endeavor to reſcue them from the ſlavery of Satan.</p>
               <p>They have moſt of them <hi>Trolles</hi> (as they call them) which are certain familiars at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending and ſerving them faithfully, giving them notice of any accident or diſtemper impending; when they ſleep theſe Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liars awake them to go a Fiſhing if the weather be fair, and if they go at any time without incouragement from them, they may ſwear all the time and catch as much Fiſh.</p>
               <p>They are ſo exquiſite in the art of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, they will ſhew ſuch ſtrangers as are curious what is done in their houſes in their own Countries; they will inform them Whether their Fathers, Mothers, Relations, or Friends (which they deſire to be aſſured of) be living or dead. They ſell Winds alſo to any body will buy them to go whither they pleaſe.
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:42107:77"/>The Commiſs. of <hi>Kirkebar</hi> (and others beſide him) told me very gravely (as he had meant I ſhould have believed him) that thoſe who are a Fiſhing at the Foot of Mount <hi>Hecla</hi> upon a day in which there happens a Battail in any part of <hi>Europe,</hi> do conſtantly ſee the Divels coming and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into that Mountain with mens ſouls upon their backs, like Bees fetching and carrying Honey upon their Thighs.</p>
               <p>If it falls out any of their friends are dead, and they are concerned to know what is become of them, applying themſelves to theſe Sorcerers, the defunct preſently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears very melancholly and out of humour aſſures them for certain he is dead, and with the Divel (who he muſt confeſs is none of the beſt Maſters) deſires them not to trouble themſelves any more for him, for he is ſetled in <hi>Hecla,</hi> and till they come, to him can injoy them no more.</p>
               <p>The Fields in Iſland (though fair &amp; full of paſturage) cannot produce wheat or any other grain proper for bread, in reſpect of the extream coldneſs of the place, by the means of a ſharp <hi>North-Eaſt</hi> wind with which they are perpetually infeſted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="chapter">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:42107:77"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIV.</hi> The Authors departure with the reſt of the <hi>Danes from Cape Hori.</hi> Their arrival at <hi>Copenhagen</hi> and the preſent made by the Northern Company of two <hi>Sea-Horſes</hi> Horns, which were accepted for <hi>Unicorns.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THree days after we were arrived from our journy to <hi>Hecla</hi> to our Ships which was the 22th of <hi>September,</hi> a <hi>N:</hi> wind blowing favourable for us, we weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Anchor and departed, ſteering our Courſe <hi>S. S. E.</hi> Having ſail'd for ſome days indifferently well, on a ſuddain we were ſurpriſed with a ſmart Gale from the <hi>N. N. W.</hi> which drove us upon the Coaſt of <hi>Norway,</hi> where (knowing the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montories of <hi>Talſo,</hi> which is a little Town upon an eminence with a very ſtrong Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, about four Leagues from the Sea) we were overjoyed, as hoping ere long our Voyage would be at end. But we recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned without our Hoſt, for we had not been twelve hours upon the Coaſt, but the wind changed with the Moon, and forc'd us again to Sea, to avoid the Rocks, and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:42107:78"/>the danger of being driven back, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed could all the care and pains we could take prevent our running back above forty Leagues; after the Storm was over, we happened to be calmed which retard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us for ſome time; in the interim we perceived to the <hi>S. S. W.</hi> of us a great <hi>Seilon</hi> which affrighted our Seamen very much, and obliged them with all ſpeed to ſlscken their Sails, and bring them to the Maſts, leaſt otherwiſe it ſhould break up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, but it came not within two Leagues of us, at which diſtance we diſcerned it to fall. Theſe <hi>Seilons</hi> are a kind of black thick Clouds in the faſhion of Pillars, which are many times viſible at Sea, and if at any time they fall upon a Ship, it deſtroys it by the abundance of water wherewith it fils it, and ſinks it down right to the bottom, if it breaks perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicularly over it. The Calm being gone, we were beholding to a <hi>N. E.</hi> wind, which in ten days time finiſhed our Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and brought us into <hi>Copen Hagen</hi> Road, where after we had ſaluted the Caſtle, we came to an Anchor, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out our long-Boats, got on ſhore as ſoon as we could.</p>
               <p>We had ſcarce got into the Town, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:42107:78"/>his Majeſty (having notice that we had brought three or four <hi>Zemblanes</hi> along with us) commanded us to Court, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impatient to ſee them. We obeyed his command, and attended with them; as ſoon as he ſaw them he fell into great admiration, both of their habit, and ſhape of their bodies. He gave order to the Governor of the Caſtle to take them into his Care, to ſee they wanted nothing that was neceſſary, and that they be taught the Language of his Country as well and conveniently as was poſſible; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which (having made us give him a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſeveral Countries we had ſeen and of the manners and cuſtomes of the people) we were permitted to take our leaves, and to wait upon the Maſters of the Company to give them an accompt of our negotiations, with which they were very well ſatisfied, and cauſed our ſhips to be brought to <hi>Chriſtian Haven</hi> (where their Store Houſes are) to be unladen there.</p>
               <p>One of the Principals of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was ordered by the reſt in all their Names to preſent his Majeſty with the two Sea-Horſes Horns which we brought home with us, which his Majeſty received
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:42107:79"/>as a moſt ineſtimable preſent, ſuppoſing they had been Unicorns Horns, of the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of which ſo many Authors had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. He ordered them preſently to be laid up among the beſt of his Rarities, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed the Company to do them what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifit he could, and preſented the bearer with a Chain of Gold with his Picture hanging at it, and forgave him his Cuſtomes beſides.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLV.</hi> Vulgar Error about the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn and the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of its Horn.</head>
               <p>BEing upon the Subject of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn,</hi> whoſe Horn is ſo precious for the great Virtues which are attributed to it, I ſhall ſay 'tis a very difficult thing to know what Creature the right Unicorn is, there being ſeveral Animals the Greeks call <hi>Monoceros,</hi> and the Latines <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni-Cornis;</hi> as among four footed Beaſts, ſeveral <hi>Aſſes</hi> wild <hi>Oxen,</hi> and the <hi>Bull</hi> in <hi>Florida.</hi> Among Serpents, there is the horned <hi>Aſpic</hi> and the red <hi>Salamander.</hi> Among Fiſh the <hi>Piraſſocpi,</hi> the Sea-<hi>Elephant,</hi> the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:42107:79"/>Sea-<hi>Horſe,</hi> the <hi>Caſpile,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>telef.</hi> There are likewiſe of them among the Fouls, and among infects that kind of Beetle (which is frequent in <hi>Flanders, England</hi> and <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardy</hi>) called the flying <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn,</hi> beſides other Creatures of different ſpecies which are found in great numbers in the Indies.</p>
               <p>Some will have this <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn</hi> to be a Land Creature, ſome a Water, and ſome an <hi>Amphibium,</hi> as living in both.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaies that the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn</hi> is exactly like an <hi>Ox</hi> ſpotted with white, only the foot is firm and round as a <hi>Horſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Munſter</hi> will have it like a three-year-old-<hi>Colt,</hi> of a <hi>Weeſel</hi> colour, the head like a <hi>Stag,</hi> the legs ſlender, and feet clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, with his Horn in the middle of his Forehead, about two cubits in length.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marcus Paulus</hi> the <hi>Venetian</hi> affirms it to be like an <hi>Elephant,</hi> of the ſame ſhape and colour, only a little leſs, and the Tail like an <hi>Oxes;</hi> the head like a <hi>Pigs,</hi> but ſo weighty it hangs always towards the ground.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philoſtratus</hi> deſcribes it in the head like a Dragon, with a Horn (but of no great bigneſs) in the midſt of it, wreathed like a Snail, it has a beard on its Chin: a long neck, feet like a <hi>Lion,</hi> the reſt of
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:42107:80"/>its body like a <hi>Stag,</hi> and the skin like a <hi>Serpent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heſiodorus</hi> repreſents it ſo ſwift, it is not poſſible to be taken by all the Art the Huntsman can uſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis Paradis</hi> reports, that when any of themare taken, they feed them with <hi>Peas, Lintels</hi> and <hi>Beans.</hi> That they are as tall as <hi>Iriſh-Greyhounds,</hi> but not ſo ſlenderly made their hair of the colour of a <hi>Beaver</hi> very ſmooth, the neck thin, the legs and feet and tail like a <hi>Hind,</hi> the head ſhort and lean, the mouth like a <hi>Calf,</hi> the eyes large, the ears ſmall and betwixt them a Horn very ſlick, of a dark brown colour without, and about a foot in length.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thevetus;</hi> maintains the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn</hi> to be as big as an <hi>Ox</hi> at ſix Months old, with legs and feet like an Aſs, ear'd like a <hi>Rein</hi> Deer, and bears its Horn upon the top of its head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis de Barthene</hi> will have it like a <hi>Bay-Horſe,</hi> only the feet cloven, and a Horn in the middle of his forehead.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Volneſius</hi> affirms the <hi>Rhinoceros</hi> to be the right <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn, Garcius</hi> the <hi>Camphur,</hi> and <hi>John Corbichon</hi> the <hi>Egliceron</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Albertus</hi> ſaies the true <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorns</hi> Horn is a hand and a half broad at the bottome,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:42107:80"/>and ten foot long. <hi>Lewis Barthenus</hi> will have it three fathom. <hi>Munſter</hi> three Cubits. <hi>Marcus Paulus</hi> two, <hi>Lewis Paradis</hi> a foot and half. <hi>Nicholas</hi> the <hi>Venetian</hi> a a foot, and <hi>Cardan</hi> but three fingers long.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pliny</hi> repreſents the Horn black: <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus</hi> purple: <hi>Paradis</hi> of the colour of <hi>Rhubarb</hi> newly broken: <hi>Albertus</hi> of a Stags colour, and others are as obſtinate that 'tis whiter then <hi>Ivory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When I conſider the diſcrepancy in the opinions of all Authors about this <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corus horn,</hi> ſome deſcribing it one way, and ſome another, I am perſwaded my ſelf they have treated of it either out of Envy, or emulation to make themſelves admir'd, and the learned <hi>Baccius</hi> confirms that perſwaſion, aſſerting that ſuch Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors are not to be credited, as knowing nothing of that Creature but by hear-ſay, no body having ever ſeen it, any more than a <hi>Phenix.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the virtue of this <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorns horn</hi> ſuppoſe it as is reported, and thoſe they would put upon us were right, I am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured it has no more than in the Horn of a ſtag, <hi>Goat,</hi> or a piece of <hi>Ivory,</hi> which is many times uſed to ſtop the ſpitting of blood, Emrades, and looſneſs, which
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:42107:81"/>they cure by a reſtringent virtue (or rather a convenient malignity) that reſtringen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy cauſed by the Earthineſs of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) ſtopping and choking up the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in the Veins and Arteries, becomes rather a poiſon than a Cordial, like the ſtone of a certain Counſellors Clerk made up of <hi>Sulfure</hi> and <hi>Vitriol,</hi> which caſt into twenty Buckets of River water gave it a tincture and quality proper as he pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for all kinds of diſeaſes; as many Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanks do now with their powders of precious ſtones, Pearls, and Gold, which they cry up for great Antidores, whereas all experienced Phyſitians do know they are but cheats and if they give eaſe at any time 'tis more by the virtue of the thing in which it is given, than any propriety of its own; and the reaſon they give is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe nothing that is incapable of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nouriſhment, can be capable of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it, as pearl, pretious ſtones, and Gold; which if indued with any nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faculty, rich men would never die of hunger as long as they laſted, nor any Famine happen to them, as it did in the Siege of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> forty years after the death of our Saviour, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> affirms in his Hiſtory of the <hi>Jews,</hi> quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:42107:81"/>to the ſentiment of <hi>Gabriel de Caſtagne</hi> and others of his <hi>Cabal,</hi> who maintain that Gold taken in wardly is one of the greateſt antidotes in the world, though in truth it is poiſon rather, as may be prov'd by the ſmell and ſteam of it, which ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently kills the Miners as they are at work.</p>
               <p>And as a further evidence that the horn of an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn</hi> has no virtue in it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is no Cordial, it has neither taſt nor ſmell more than a bone, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence no more virtue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVI.</hi> The Authors reflections upon an Error in our <hi>Geographers</hi> in the placing of <hi>Greenland</hi> and <hi>Zembla,</hi> with Obſervations upon ſuch as have writ about <hi>Voygat,</hi> and the <hi>Samojedes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT my return from thoſe Northern Countries, there having fallen into my hands ſeveral Geografical Charts, of ſundry eminent and much celebrated Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, I was amazed to ſee how as it were unanimouſly) they were miſtaken in the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:42107:82"/>poſition of <hi>Zembla,</hi> which they place much nearer the North Pole, than really it is, and <hi>N. E.</hi> of <hi>Laponia</hi> though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is more inclining to the North. They divide it likewiſe by the Sea from <hi>Greenland,</hi> and put it at above twelve hundred Leagues diſtance from it, when as indeed thoſe two Countries are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous, the Coaſts of <hi>Greenland</hi> butting upon the Coaſts of <hi>Zembla,</hi> ſo as did not the great quantity of Snow, and the violence of the Cold render thoſe borders uninhabitable, the paſſage would be very eaſie by Land from <hi>Greenland</hi> to <hi>Zembla,</hi> and from <hi>Zembla</hi> (paſſing the <hi>Patenoſtres</hi> Mountains) to enter into <hi>Samoſeſpia;</hi> from thence into <hi>Tartary,</hi> or <hi>Muſcovy</hi> as one pleas'd.</p>
               <p>I was amazed likewiſe to ſee they had deſcrib'd the <hi>Strait</hi> called <hi>Voygat</hi> not above ten French Leagues in length wheras it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains above five &amp; thirty Dutch Leagues, which is ſix times as much; again they would perſwade us that thorow that ſtrait our Ships might paſs into the great <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian</hi> Ocean, which is a a miſtake, though they indeed do affirm that in the time of Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> of <hi>Naſſau</hi> a Dutch Veſſel paſſed that way into that Ocean, but it
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:42107:82"/>is a manifeſt errour, that ſtrait being bounded (as I ſaid before) by the <hi>Patenoſtres</hi> Mountains, the leaſt of which is above halfe a League high, and the tops of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> covered with perpetual Snow which never diſſloves. And of this I can give a poſitive Teſtimony having been my ſelf in that ſtrait, under thoſe Mountains in the dog-days (which is the hotteſt time in the year) and found it very cold, the winter continuing all the year in thoſe parts, as the Summer does about the <hi>Magellan</hi> Straits near the <hi>Antartick</hi> Pole.</p>
               <p>As the Countries remote towards the <hi>South,</hi> are called <hi>incognitae:</hi> ſo the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries in the ſame diſtance, might have the ſame appellation; yet though to us they are unknown at preſent, I do not queſtion but if we had occaſion to go farther, we ſhould diſcover Countries well peopled and inhabited, which we might call new Worlds, according to the example of <hi>Chriſtopher Columbus, Magellan,</hi> and others who have called their diſcoveries by that Title, following therein ſentiments of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocritus Epienrus</hi> and <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> who maintain there are ſeveral Worlds, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine of <hi>Hermes Triſme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtus</hi>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:42107:83"/>and <hi>Plato,</hi> who affirm there is but one which God created according to his own pleaſure, of which no man can give an account, either of its end, beginning, height, depth, or middle: though our <hi>Geographers</hi> tell us other things in their <hi>Planiſphers,</hi> propoſing the <hi>Artick</hi> Pole for the Top, the <hi>Antartick</hi> for the bottom, and the <hi>Equator</hi> for the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle. To which <hi>Strabo</hi> diſſents, aſſerting the middle of the World to be the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> in <hi>Greece. Beroſus,</hi> the Mountain <hi>Arrarat</hi> in <hi>Armenia,</hi> and ſeveral others will have it <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would fain know of our <hi>Geographers</hi> where they place the old <hi>Zembla;</hi> I am of opinion if they had been in the new, they would confeſs there was no other. That New <hi>Holland, Weſt-Friezeland,</hi> and <hi>Cape d'Hyver</hi> are in the Straits of <hi>Voygat,</hi> and not on the other ſide in the great <hi>Tartarean</hi> Ocean as they have placed them. And he (that in his relation of the State of <hi>Muſcovy</hi> ſpeaks of the <hi>Samojedes</hi>) if he had been among them, and had any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation there, would not have deſcrib'd them eaters of ſtrangers, and that the Grand Duke ſent his <hi>Criminals</hi> thither, to be devoured by them which is utterly falſe;
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:42107:83"/>Though their Bodies are ill favoured, and their wit dull, though they have no knowledge of God, nor fear of torment in the other World; (believing their ſouls and bodies die together) though they ſeem the miſerableſt people of the Earth, living in Summer upon <hi>Bears, Woolfs, Foxes, Crowes, Eagles,</hi> and other wild Creatures which they hunt firſt and then eat in their <hi>Cabanes</hi> broild upon the Coals, and ſubſiſt in the Winter upon nothing but Fiſh dried in the Sun in the Summer time, unleſs by accident they kill ſome of thoſe Bears, who (having nothing left by the Snow in the fields) come home to their Cabanes to devour them. Notwithſtanding all theſe inconveniencies, they are naturally hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, receiving ſtrangers like themſelves, without doing them any injury; for, though they appear cruel and barbarous, they are honeſt and ſincere, which is very much conſidering they are Neighbours to the worſt people in the world, which are the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and <hi>Tingorſes,</hi> with whom they have as great traffick and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on that ſide, as they have with the <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berians, Borandines,</hi> and <hi>Laplanders</hi> on the other.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
